<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://insideretail.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://insideretail.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-06-08T13:53:30+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/</id><title type="html">Inside Retail</title><subtitle>The online destination for independent retailers. Whether you sell on the high street or online, are just getting started or tweaking the dream, you can find stories, tips, interviews and inspiration to help accelerate the growth of your business.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ready For Growth?</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/ready-for-growth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ready For Growth?" /><published>2017-06-06T05:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-06-06T05:20:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/ready-for-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/ready-for-growth/">&lt;p&gt;Independent retailers across the UK face a host of challenges and obstacles each and every day which can limit growth potential and often leave you feeling unsure of what the best steps towards growth are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Retail has conducted research into over 200 retailers like yourself from across the UK and we’ve found there are some recurring key challenges to achieving your business ambition. These challenges often include;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving traffic to your website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using social media to increase customer numbers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating work-life balance, and good business time management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving footfall to your shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing products which sell fast at full price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help address these issues and equip dynamic business leaders with the support they need to achieve their retail growth ambitions, we here at Inside Retail have teamed up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://g.grantthornton.co.uk/about-us/&quot;&gt;G by Grant Thornton&lt;/a&gt; to develop The Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;download-the-programme-prospectus-for-all-the-info-here&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the programme prospectus for all the info here:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Retail Growth Programme detailed flyer 02.pdf&quot; class=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Download Brochure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed specifically for retailers, the Retail Growth Programme helps you plan and achieve the future growth ambitions you want for your business and for yourself.
The programme is designed with the leader of retail businesses in mind; providing practical tools, plans and best practices that will help to facilitate rapid and sustainable business growth. During the year you will develop your knowledge in key areas to deliver your business goals: creating plans, networks and connections that will contribute to your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;g-helped-us-reconnect-with-our-purpose-and-strengths-as-well-as-realising-our-fuller-potential-with-regards-to-our-offering&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“G HELPED US RECONNECT WITH OUR PURPOSE AND STRENGTHS AS WELL AS REALISING OUR FULLER POTENTIAL WITH REGARDS TO OUR OFFERING.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asra Ali-Khan,
Managing Director, Liquid TV&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAND OUT FROM THE CROWD AND ACHIEVE RAPID AND SUSTAINABLE GROWTH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to learn, adopt new practices and develop personally are critical to business success. These newly adopted skills, applied to your business through clearly actionable plans, can set you apart in a crowded market, providing the catalyst for rapid and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme provides a unique opportunity for you to step back from the day-to-day demands of running your business, giving you the clarity and the time to develop a detailed, actionable plan for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The benefits:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accelerated growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A robust and rigorous plan for growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More confidence and increased focus on priorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The path to improved profitability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More effective leadership and management skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drawing on the collective skills and knowledge of Grant Thornton’s extensive network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Retail Growth Programme is built around a series of growth workshops where you will develop and implement your growth strategy for your business. The programme is modular and allows you to continually apply your learning to how you run your business while you participate. The programme runs over 12 months. In between each workshop, you will continue working on developing and implementing your own growth strategy for your business, making immediate improvements every month.
Throughout the programme, you will be supported by an experienced account manager who works with you to ensure that you get the maximum value from your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who is it for?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambitious businesses in the retail sector&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it cost?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£5,000 + VAT (payable £1,250 + VAT per quarter)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does it take place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One monthly session in either London or Birmingham with support via phone and email across the duration of the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-12-month-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YOUR 12 MONTH PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH SUPPORT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic conversation and growth reviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dedicated account manager providing coaching and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly Peer Boards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly insights on key sectors and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH WORKSHOPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ten specially designed growth workshops for you to choose from a selection of sixteen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going International&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Merchandising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operations and Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customer and Sales Profiling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engaging and Retaining Talent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reaching the Market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing the Next Location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retail Space Design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulations and Legislation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financing Growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme is designed for retailers or those looking to diversify into the retail sector. If you are already successfully trading and want to take the next step towards your future ambitions and growth, please get in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;click-here-to-find-out-more-about-the-g-by-grant-thornton-retail-growth-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the G by Grant Thornton Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html">Independent retailers across the UK face a host of challenges and obstacles each and every day which can limit growth potential and often leave you feeling unsure of what the best steps towards growth are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lessons learned from taking the plunge into menswear</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/lessons-learned-from-taking-the-plunge-into-menswear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lessons learned from taking the plunge into menswear" /><published>2017-05-29T05:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-29T05:16:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/lessons-learned-from-taking-the-plunge-into-menswear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/lessons-learned-from-taking-the-plunge-into-menswear/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last week we explored the things to consider if you’re thinking about branching out into the rapidly growing &lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/how-about-menswear-what-to-consider-when-expanding-into-menswear/&quot;&gt;menswear&lt;/a&gt; market. Now we’re able to share a real example of that diversification process.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have decided to expand into menswear to make the most of the growing market but how exactly do you go about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Retail caught up with Georgie Power, co-founder of north-east London indie The Hub, to find out what they have learned from taking the plunge into menswear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power and her sister Louise opened their first store – a womenswear retailer – in Stoke Newington in 2002 and two years later opened a standalone menswear shop after a strong demand from the local men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A man’s world&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first the sisters felt like they were operating in a man’s world where even the trade shows were “blokey”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We were two women who had a background in womenswear and it was quite difficult at first,” says Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They now have a menswear manager and buyer who began working for them as a Saturday Boy, who helps provide a man’s perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes we get it wrong as two women and it is good to have a man on board,” explains Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub went from strength to strength and opened a third store in nearby Broadway Market in 2011, which sells both menswear and womenswear in the same store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We think it is really nice to have it combined,” says Power. If the opportunity arose they would snap up a larger store in Stoke Newington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/HUB-SHOP-MENSWEAR-.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;HUB-SHOP-MENSWEAR-.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting the balance right&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mix of product in the Broadway Market store is a 65-35 split in favour of womenswear, which reflects overall sales. The shop’s existing design lent itself to selling menswear and womenswear in two distinct areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We sometimes think about ‘what if you blend the ranges together?’ but I think it does throw people a little bit if it is not so obvious, it can confuse people,” says Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The menswear is displayed in the front of the store because Power says you sometimes have to make it “a bit more obvious” to lure men in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power believes men “like it simple” when it comes to displaying stock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We find that if too much is folded on a shelf they don’t look at it, it almost has to be easy access, they’ve got to be able to get it off the rail and probably too much [stock] is a bit overwhelming,” says Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The generation gap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She believes how men approach shopping depends on their age with those under 45 much more willing to engage, while there is a growing trend towards men shopping with their male friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, women still buy a lot of clothes for their partners and Power believes as much as 50% of sales in the menswear-only shop comes from women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“At the end of the day women still shop more than men,” says Power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hitting the right note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music plays a big part in catering for the male customer and can be used to create a relaxed atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hub hired an independent music consultant to create a women’s and men’s playlist, but the female staff decided they prefer the men’s playlist so they’ve told the consultant they want all the music to be a “bit more unisex”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Girls do not notice the music as much, it is all about the whole shopping experience,” says Power. “But guys are a little bit geeky and they will ask what the track is.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Broadway Market shop they have the same consistent décor throughout and Power says no one is bothered by having unisex changing rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating an all-round experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Space constraints have prevented The Hub dabbing with the likes of pop-up barber shops and coffee areas that are now de mode in concept menswear shops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, for those with limited space Power recommends little touches that enhance the whole experience and encourage men to stay longer. This could include a comfy chair for them to sit on while they try on shoes or ensuring you have free magazines to browse through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male grooming products and dark chocolate are also proving popular. This is all geared towards constantly evolving to create an irresistible all-round lifestyle experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Power believes the key is to never stop thinking of and discussing improvements to the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You can’t rest on your laurels,” concludes Power.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="instore" /><category term="Inspiration" /><summary type="html">Last week we explored the things to consider if you’re thinking about branching out into the rapidly growing menswear market. Now we’re able to share a real example of that diversification process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experiencing pop-ups is an emerging trend in retail – Case study</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/experiencing-pop-ups-is-an-emerging-trend-in-retail-case-study/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experiencing pop-ups is an emerging trend in retail – Case study" /><published>2017-05-26T13:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-26T13:17:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/experiencing-pop-ups-is-an-emerging-trend-in-retail-case-study</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/experiencing-pop-ups-is-an-emerging-trend-in-retail-case-study/">&lt;p&gt;For emerging brands, and retailers that have an online presence only, the concept of running an actual ‘bricks and mortar’ store can be daunting. Pop-up stores present a unique and creative opportunity to test location and new products, and give you a taster of who your customers could be, before committing to a lengthy lease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Janine Dewey opened her first store in 2005, and with over a decade of experience as an independent fashion retailer, now runs her store as a pop-up store for 8-9 months of the year.
Janine’s passion for the fashion industry and commitment to her business, together with the support of her husband and a loyal team, has contributed to success of this unique business model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Keefe Fashion is a unique fashion destination in Surrey with prestigious awards including Drapers Fashion Awards Finalist in 2012, Drapers Footwear &amp;amp; Accessories Finalist in 2013, and being voted 14th in Vogue’s top 100 stores outside London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Janine explained that communication was a key aspect to the success of this business model, by ensuring her customers and the brands she collaborates with, are informed about the store’s seasonal operations. Janine utilises the additional quarter of the year to source new collections and new brands to keep things fresh for her customers. Her blog keeps customers engaged and inspired through photographs and experiences from her overseas trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By altering the way she does business, Janine’s decision to operate O’Keefe Fashion as a pop-up has paid off, with a loyal customer base who return not just for the great clothes, but for the personal service which includes genuine advice, special orders, home delivery and urgent alterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the months she is not there, Janine leases out the store, enabling emerging brands and retailers across different industries to benefit from a unique experience to test new products and a new location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So renting short-term retail space doesn’t have to be daunting, and there are plenty of opportunities across the country to seek out a pop-up location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We caught up with Janine with a quick fire round of questions relating to fashion and retail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who is your fashion icon?
Diane Keaton (Annie Hall and still actually).
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Diane_Keaton_2012-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Diane_Keaton_2012-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Favourite trend or era?
NOW…..I love the mash up, a new approach to fashion this season, mixing prints and colours…Be bold.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What are your Spring/Summer wardrobe essentials?
Linen is my go to favourite summer fabric. We are carrying our own premium linen collection this summer and almost sold out already.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who, or what do you follow on social media?
A mixture of fashion, interior design, food and my gorgeous mates….my best inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Favourite fashion magazine, blog +/or website?
Always VOGUE magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Who is your customer?
My customers are a real cross section of ages and sizes, and they love the eclectic brand mix we carry.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do they love about you and your store?
My customers love that we are very much a lifestyle store and focus on unique bohemian inspired day and evening wear. Our own brand cashmere and linen dress collection is proving to be very popular this season as it is totally exclusive to our store.
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/IMG_4641.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_4641.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’s on the playlist in store today?
Guilty Secret…HARRY STYLES…..we LOVE his new single.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How do you and your team create a better shopping experience for your customer?
Laughter, fun, sincerity and time…the collections look after themselves then.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most desired piece instore?
Suzy D lounge pants. We sell about 300 pairs a season!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Best piece of advice?
Care about your customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most important form of support or advice when running your own business?
Family first, and honest feedback from customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Biggest day of sales?
£9,000….Woohoo!!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This month’s activity to drive customers in store?
Introducing our own label, it’s been a huge success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One goal for 2017
Expanding our own label.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Onechallenge for 2017
Beating previous year’s turnover.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Thoughts on the future of retailing?
Review your seasonal brand mix sell through, introduce new brands and improve marketing.
&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/IMG_3299.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_3299.JPG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/Janine-O'Keefe-2012.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Janine-O'Keefe-2012.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">For emerging brands, and retailers that have an online presence only, the concept of running an actual ‘bricks and mortar’ store can be daunting. Pop-up stores present a unique and creative opportunity to test location and new products, and give you a taster of who your customers could be, before committing to a lengthy lease.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">‘How about menswear? : What to consider when expanding into menswear’</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/how-about-menswear-what-to-consider-when-expanding-into-menswear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘How about menswear? : What to consider when expanding into menswear’" /><published>2017-05-26T12:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-26T12:05:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/how-about-menswear-what-to-consider-when-expanding-into-menswear</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/how-about-menswear-what-to-consider-when-expanding-into-menswear/">&lt;p&gt;Large brands and big name designers are scrambling to launch menswear and it is a bandwagon that indies would also be wise to jump on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global Data forecasts menswear growth will increase quicker both this year and next with growth in the market set to hit 3.4% year-on-year in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Kors, New Look, Lululemon and Stella McCartney are among the large retailers and designers that are tapping into the trend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the move from womenswear to menswear is no easy task and there have been plenty of failures along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maureen Hinton, retail analyst at Global Data, says that if you are an indie retailer with a couple of stores you need to think hard to “determine exactly who you are targeting”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, an indie in London’s Stoke Newington would “probably be looking for quirkier brands, smaller and up and coming brands”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consideration must also be given about whether to launch menswear in your existing womenswear store, or to open another location for expanding into the new product category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mixing the two is a bit difficult,” says Hinton. “It depends on the profile of your brand really, if it is too feminine it is going to be more difficult to introduce menswear.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Akshara Manohar, strategist at retail and brand consultancy Fitch, agrees with Hinton that striking the right balance is of the utmost importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She believes that if 80% of merchandise is womenswear then an effective strategy is to pepper the remaining 20% of men’s product throughout the store to take advantage of women shoppers wanting to gift for the men in their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you are making a commitment to a 50-50 split between men’s and women’s products then Manohar advises having two separate split zones or even standalone stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our sensibilities are very different,” says Manohar. “I might gravitate towards different textures, materials and colours and finishes whereas men would gravitate towards completely different things.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She adds that there is more to the store design than simply having exposed brickwork for the men’s area and softer furnishings for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It is completely sensorial,” says Manohar. “It is the sound, the colours, the tones, the staff, and even the smells.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manohar believes the key is to create an environment where men can “walk in confidently and have a good time”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because of the different mindsets of men and women. While women are happy to “forage” for clothes this can be a more intimidating process for men, according to Manohar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One thing that seems to be putting off all men is the clutter” says Manohar. “Less is more for them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By de-cluttering the men’s department retailers are able to make it an open and easy atmosphere to engage in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To come into a store is a big effort so you need to make that experience worthwhile or they will be unlikely to return,” says Manohar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the formula can be cracked, then indies are onto a winner because men tend to show more loyalty to brands because once they find something they like they are happy to stick with it for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way Manohar believes men can be hooked in is by taking a leaf out of Lululemon’s book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lululemon has a reputation for being a retailer of women’s yoga clothes but is increasingly moving into menswear, and the latest step is through its &lt;a href=&quot;http://info.lululemon.com/about/media/lululemon-opens-mens-local-in-toronto&quot;&gt;menswear store in Canada&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes a pop-up barber shop and areas where customers can play ping pong or have a coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such concept stores are perhaps hard for indies to emulate but should certainly provide inspiration in how to tap into the lucrative but arguably less adventurous male customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is no one size fits all answer,” concludes Manohar. “Traditionally shopping has been perceived as a feminine activity and retailers previously catered only for women and did not cater to the nuances of the male shopper”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time for retailers to put the male shopper at the forefront of their strategy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="instore" /><summary type="html">Large brands and big name designers are scrambling to launch menswear and it is a bandwagon that indies would also be wise to jump on.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bringing spandex back: Everything you need to know about athleisure</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/bringing-spandex-back-everything-you-need-to-know-about-athleisure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing spandex back: Everything you need to know about athleisure" /><published>2017-05-22T12:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-22T12:31:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/bringing-spandex-back-everything-you-need-to-know-about-athleisure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/bringing-spandex-back-everything-you-need-to-know-about-athleisure/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-athleisure&quot;&gt;What is athleisure?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you thought lycra was something we left in the ‘90s then think again. “Athleisure”, which refers to the rise of comfortable, casual clothing that is also fashionable, has become such a big deal that the word has found its way into the Oxford English dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leggings, and even jeggings, need no longer be peeled off after a gym session but can worn proudly to brunch afterwards — or even teamed with a pair of heels at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-has-it-become-a-thing&quot;&gt;Why has it become a “thing”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fashion business has caught onto the fact that men and women want to look stylish while they sweat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did they work this out? Well, Gigi Hadid, Beyonce and the Kardashian clan have gone a long way to promoting the cause by showing that loungewear worn creatively (paired variously with bomber jackets, sunnies, an oversized tee or some bling) can be seriously fierce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of social media cannot be ignored when it comes to the rise of athleisure. Instagram influencers clutching green juices while wearing cutting edge activewear has fuelled the trend hugely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big sportswear brands have been quick to respond and so have the fashionistas, such as Givenchy’s Ricardo Tisci designing capsule collections for Nike and Stella McCartney’s continuing collaboration with Adidas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whos-buying-it&quot;&gt;Who’s buying it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gym bunnies aren’t your only potential clientele. The beauty of athleisure is that it is starting to extend into other areas of modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you have access to customers who are professionals, parents, bright young things or anyone who likes to look good while they race around at speed, then you should stock athleisure. Or perhaps even buy a range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is now a billion-dollar industry globally and is showing no sign of slowing despite having first emerged in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year retailers across the Britain and America increased their activewear offerings by 22 per cent, leading to a 27 per cent jump in full-priced sell outs, according to research company Edited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sales of&lt;a href=&quot;https://fashionunited.uk/news/fashion/women-say-farewell-to-heels-and-hello-to-comfy-trainers/2016093021985&quot;&gt; trainers have already overtaken heels&lt;/a&gt; in the UK and athleisure is giving the (seriously bullish) denim industry a run for its money as consumers reject skinny jeans in favour of leggings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even China, a key market indicator for luxury, is going casual with sales of&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-06-14/nike-adidas-replace-big-name-luxury-as-china-goes-casual&quot;&gt; Adidas growing 38 per cent to $2.7 billion last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;will-it-still-be-important-next-year&quot;&gt;Will it still be important next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, says Tully Lou, an Australian health and wellness blogger turned athleisure designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Athleisure is not a fad, it’s a lifestyle. It is just going to continue to grow especially where activewear merges into streetwear,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s comfortable and trans-seasonal so you get your money’s worth. I’ve also seen it slowly creeping into the workplace as well. Functional and stylish will be the way of the future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-products-are-going-to-be-big-in-springsummer-2018&quot;&gt;What products are going to be big in Spring/Summer 2018?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The industry is predicting that we will reach peak legging in 2017. But crop tops, trainers and anything in bright colours and zingy patterns will be a good bet to stock for next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Expect more of a unisex vibe so you can throw on your boyfriend’s sweater but it still looks stylish paired with a pair of leggings, killer kicks and a leather jacket,” says Lou.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-styled “athleisure expert” and&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/hopescopeofficial/?hl=en&quot;&gt; Instagram influencer Hope Allen&lt;/a&gt; agrees. “I predict that over the next 12 months we’ll see a shift from neutrals, earthy tones and monochrome colour schemes towards bold patterns and bright colours,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Matching tracksuits and platform heels will also be making a comeback as a major trend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-forget-the-men&quot;&gt;Don’t forget the men&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While women undoubtedly dominate this sector if you’re buying a range you’d be foolish to forget about the men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will the boys be wearing? “A tailored pair of chinos and a really good quality slim tee in three no fail colours: black, white and grey/marle,” says Lou.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can stay on top of the latest trends by keeping a close eye on Instagram and there are lots of other &lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves/&quot;&gt;tips here .&lt;/a&gt; But this can be hard work and will mean the trend is already making its way to mainstream which leaves you rushing to place orders in time. A savvy option would be to check out the trade shows for a look at costs and styles whilst gathering as much free info as you can from trend forecasters like WGSN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pure is coming up in July and stocks a curated athleisure range. You can also attend free seminars at the show from WGSN which will cover next year’s trends in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Inspiration" /><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">What is athleisure?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Do Big Retailers Fear? You!</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Do Big Retailers Fear? You!" /><published>2017-05-05T12:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-05T12:38:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you/">&lt;p&gt;I visited the World Retail Congress in Dubai to see what the world’s leading retailers are up to, and how they feel about their own progress in giving modern customers what they want. I went because although the growth strategy for Calvin Klein is a long way from that of my local independent boutique in Oxfordshire, I wanted to see what we, in the Independent Retail community could learn from the biggest and best. I also suspected there might be opportunities discussed that smaller retailers are best placed to take advantage of, and I wasn’t wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away really excited despite the fact that brands like Macy’s, Marks and Spencer and lots of the other retailers present, are having a nightmare keeping up with customers changing demands. My unseemly optimism was down to things I heard constantly repeated during the event: The key to sustainable retail is catering to young consumers who want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An experience. Might be emotional, might be entertaining, but not just ‘stuff’, it might even be that your products deliver this by having a story of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A sense of place, a local connection. A shop that’s a part of a community, perhaps with products that are linked to the area, perhaps an online shop with a strong regional personality&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A personal service. People who say hello, emails that tell your best customers when they’re favourite soap has been delivered, packaging that says thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge stores like Waterstones are opening pretend independent shops to imitate those things and all progressive multinational retailers are spending huge sums on their customer data, so that they can create the impression of personal engagement. Actual indies have this already, and this presents  a huge opportunity to make the most of what comes naturally to them and use it to become a destination in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waterstones actually had a great year, despite Amazon’s total domination of the book market, by using their experience and book recommendations to stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inspiration from larger retailers on elements you might want to adapt for your own store, follow the advice of Martin Newman Founder of famous consultancy Practicology, and check out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pages.rapha.cc/clubs&quot;&gt;Rapha&lt;/a&gt;. The cycle retailer has styled its stores a club houses and offers an amazing array of events, a real sense of community. Revenues areup 30% on the previous 12 months, so what they’re doing is obviously working.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jo Malone’s new store, Jo Loves. 92% of people who took part in her Perfume Painting experience went on to make a purchase. Take a look at her &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joloves.com/experiences&quot;&gt;new initiatives&lt;/a&gt; for inspiration on making your store an unexpected delight for customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ability to change direction and respond to the customer, at speeds that large retailers can only dream of, indies are perfectly placed to offer the kind of retail experience consumers want. I know it’s very difficult to take time away from the day to day management to look at how to develop your store, or in the words of Exec Director of M&amp;amp;S Patrick Bousquet-Chavanne, answer the question, “What do you want to be when you grow up”;. But the rapid changes in the industry have created an opportunity, and it’s important to take it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve picked out five of the most important quotes I heard during the congress. I hope you find them useful. If you’d like us to follow up on any of these topics to get more detail for you, email me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“A customer who engages with us on more than one platform is 5 times more valuable to us than one who only engages with us on one” Terry Lundgren, Chairman, Macy’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that if one of your customers likes your Facebook post and buys then something from you in-store for instance, that person is much more likely to buy from you again, and to spend more than if they’d only popped into the shop. You could use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pinterest, Facebook, Instagram,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An online store, a pop up shop,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A guest blog/ Q&amp;amp;A on a local publication,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Events in your garden centre&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sponsorship of your local football team.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are loads of different ways to give your potential customers an opportunity to build trust in and interest in your shop. None of which require a Macy’s budget and 728 stores!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“When we opened Bloomingdales in Kuwait we made it a women-only store. This was controversial and took a lot of convincing the board but it’s highly successful. Don’t be afraid to take a risk if you know what your customers want” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessoffashion.com/community/people/khalid-al-tayer&quot;&gt;Khalid Al Tayer, CEO, Al Tayer Insignia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably not expanding to Kuwait but the willingness to listen to local customers made Bloomingdales a lot of money, so there’s no reason it can’t do the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to open a second store don’t just reproduce your product range and call it a day. Conduct local research to see if incomes, tastes, age groups etc are different. Invite yourself to local community groups – golf, mums and toddlers, WI, swing dancing and ask them what they would like to be able to buy from you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you’re sure, take a risk, whether in a new store or the existing one. If you know from your research and experience that your customers want a range of socks with flamingos, don’t buy black tights instead just to be safe, they can buy those anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tell your customers about what you’ve done for them. If you’ve opened a new shop, or taken another risk, GO BIG in telling people about it. Why you did it, how excited you are, where to buy and how, and make sure you’ve got it online! It’s where people look for new things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“83% of customers want a personalised experience” Brian Elliot, Managing Partner, McKinsey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McKinsey advise huge corporations on how to transform their businesses and Brian talked a lot about using big data to give a personal experience. The end game is a series of actions based on using customer information, to make more money for the retailers. Some key tricks the big boys use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using personalisation to shift old stock. Offer customers who have purchased a product before, a small discount before it goes on sale. Ie: ‘Mrs Jones, you bought a Cath Kidstone gardening fork from us in June. We’d like to offer you a 10% discount on the rest of the range, to give you first choice before it goes on sale’. This can help you get better margins on products prior to heavier discounting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tell people who tried to buy something, when it’s back in stock.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send people relevant content. For instance, a tip sheet you’ve written on how to style a jumpsuit for a wedding, sent to women in their 30s. Or chatting to people in-store, about the occasion they’re buying for, and making suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these work best if you have your customers email addresses or home addresses. If you don’t have those, it might be time to start thinking about how to collect them. Don’t forget though, the reason big retail focusses on email is because they cannot realistically offer a personal service instore (with new interactive changing rooms, this is just around the corner for the fashion industry). If you know your best customers by name, and/or have well trained staff, you can create a personal service, but without a system to record what your customer loves, it is difficult to keep track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“On Amazon, small no-name brands are the biggest competitors to brands like Sony and L’Oreal” Spencer Millerberg, Founder, One Click Retail.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon is a key reason for the decline of big retail and in the small retail community we need to recognise its influence without being intimidated. One Click Retail analyse product sales on Amazon. If you’re thinking about using Amazon for your own gain, here are some tips from a company that tracks how products perform on the platform. They advise companies like Unilever and Nestle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;90% of purchases begin with the search bar. Nobody chooses the ‘shop by department’ option&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To take advantage of that, describe your product using words the customer will search for eg, Soap not ‘cleansing bar (a mistake Dove made!), and fish tank rather than an aquatic orb. Good search terms result in more people to your product page, it generates traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;95% of customers look at ALL the photos and these are the best way to convert the people who visit your product page, to paying customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most customers don’t scroll down to the bottom of the product page, they just look at the top part ‘above the fold’ and all the pictures. Make sure the text and photos at the top of the listing are detailed and interesting enough that the customer can feel confident purchasing from you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on these until you’ve managed to get onto the first page of the search results will put you in a position to compete on a level playing field with enormous conglomerates. And if you’re getting good reviews there’s no reason you can’t outsell Sony!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Department Store retail now makes up 2% of the total retail market. It used to be 10% and we’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.retail-week.com/sectors/home-and-diy/big-box-little-box-cardboard-box-why-big-retailers-are-shrinking/7011157.article&quot;&gt;seen 10yrs of steady decline&lt;/a&gt;.” Robin Lewis, CEO, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therobinreport.com/&quot;&gt;The Robin Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big thing I took from this fascinating session was that ‘big stores are not cool’. As young consumers look to experience and discover things, driving to an out of town retail park and wandering around DFS doesn’t cut it. The Big Box formats are only surviving in the US (where they lead, we follow) if they operate like neighbourhoods, with sports, community, great food, farmers markets ie a Highstreet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robin said, ‘The Future of retail can be the highstreet, if it’s a good highstreet’, and he’s got a lot of data to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Independents have a better profit potential than Big Box retail. A single brand/store personality, and an intimate, social atmosphere is where the potential is. Ralph Lauren, Gap, Levi all missed the boat with this and got confusing and stale&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The small shop has better potential to offer generation Z customers want they want&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cause-based retailing really sells now, trust is important. Eg, selling a product that you know contributes to charity, or is made from waste plastic, or by disadvantaged people will appeal to young buyers. You can work with tiny, unique suppliers, big retailers cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sharing, renting and swapping are becoming very popular, small shops find it easier to offer this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bricks and mortar have the huge advantage of being able to offer an online and offline service, with customers who have access to multiple platforms spending 3,4,5 times more, this is a huge asset. Pure online retailers struggle to offer that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His parting shot. “The consumer has changed totally” Small start-ups are going to chip away at the big stores because they can’t move fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon is a big beast but it’s a great place for would be online-indie retailers to get started. Testing products, making sure you’re logistics and systems work etc, before you start to offer a full range under your own steam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Macy’s put it ‘Why would a 25 year old want to drive to an out of town store to look at a huge building filled with stuff, when they could buy it online and then go rock climbing. We need to provide an experience’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our independent shops can offer that experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get in touch with me if you’re doing a great job of making shopping fun. I’d love to interview you about what you’re up to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="inspiration" /><summary type="html">I visited the World Retail Congress in Dubai to see what the world’s leading retailers are up to, and how they feel about their own progress in giving modern customers what they want. I went because although the growth strategy for Calvin Klein is a long way from that of my local independent boutique in Oxfordshire, I wanted to see what we, in the Independent Retail community could learn from the biggest and best. I also suspected there might be opportunities discussed that smaller retailers are best placed to take advantage of, and I wasn’t wrong.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch: Learn How Independent Menswear Retailer, Number Six, Uses Customer Data</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch: Learn How Independent Menswear Retailer, Number Six, Uses Customer Data" /><published>2017-04-27T15:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-27T15:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;win-with-vend&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;WIN WITH VEND:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-here-for-your-chance-to-win-20000-worth-of-retail-technology-support-and-marketing-all-thanks-to-vend&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;Enter here for your chance to WIN £20,000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; worth of retail technology, support, and marketing all thanks to Vend.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-personal-connection-with-customers&quot;&gt;A personal connection with customers:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent retailers have always prided themselves on being close to their customers and with simple technology its possible to give your valued customers the inside scoop on new deliveries of their favourite products, personalised discounts and anything else you’d like to tell them. Everyone from John Lewis to Number Six, the indie retailer interviewed here, see immediate boosts in sales after communicating with customers so it’s well worth the effort!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting data and being able to crunch the sales numbers using data analytics has very much been the domain of larger organisations, but as these activities become essential for smaller retailers as well, new technology companies have risen to the challenge of creating great products for them. We feature Vend in this video and they’re a prime example of that trend. Their ePOS system means it is now possible for smaller retailers to cost effectively offer your customers the same service they get from the biggest names in retail, but with all the added benefits of shopping with a small independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-solutions-to-help-drive-your-business-forward&quot;&gt;Looking for solutions to help drive your business forward?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake Hardy, owner of successful menswear retailer, Number Six, shares how he easily gathers and uses customer information to offer them exactly what they’ve asked for. He shares ideas on what to send and when, to get the best up-tick in sales whilst being useful and  appealing to customers, rather than an inbox irritant. Interviewed by Sophy Searight, Editor at Inside Retail, in partnership with Vend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inside Retail are proud to have Vend on board as a partner, we share the same ambitions for a thriving high street.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;Enter to win&lt;/a&gt; and grow your retail with Vend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">WIN WITH VEND:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interiors trends for 2017 and how to style your store to increase footfall</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interiors trends for 2017 and how to style your store to increase footfall" /><published>2017-04-13T06:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T06:19:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall/">&lt;p&gt;Research interiors trends for 2017 and you’ll come up with a heady mix of foliage, natural raw materials, visceral texture and an abundance of colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds fantastic for spring. But, if I’m a retailer hoping to stock up on items that will appeal to consumers throughout the year, how is this stuff going to age?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of an independent retailer’s job is identifying the trends that are going to have long legs - and the ones to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Lisa White, head of Lifestyle &amp;amp; Interiors at WGSN, a safe option is to stick to plant life - which can bring both seasonal flair to your shop and opportunities for buyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Indoor plants are trending tremendously at the moment,” says White. She suspects that this will run and run and so advises to get potting up for both summer and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the autumn consumers like to take a bit of nature back inside with them—so this will be a good time to stock up on plant accessories,” she says. “The indoor garden is getting more glamorous and people are willing to spend a bit more money on plant accessories, for themselves and also for gifts. Think beautiful pots in interesting materials, from artisanal ceramics to brushed brass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GOING TO POT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Plant stands will also be trending - so people can put their plants on a pedestal. There will also be a continuation of hanging plants in macramé planters, but this autumn and winter they will be in more sophisticated materials and colours to bring a bit of glam to the home garden.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plants are also a great way to make your shop appear fresh. Move them about, put them in big, colourful pots and it could really increase footfall as we move from the heat of summer towards winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bring in some easy-care plants into the store to add freshness and personality,” says White. “Cacti have been popular, but if you want something different, 1970s plants will be trending [by the autumn], and they are very easy to care for: spider plants, rubber plants, pileas. You’ll find people linger longer in retail spaces that have greenery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know how to identify the key trend of the year? “It’s really useful to look at Pantone’s colour of the year. It’s starting to not just be a colour predictor but a social indicator as well,” says trend consultant Louise Healy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pantone describes its annual selection as “a colour snapshot of what we see taking place in our global culture that serves as an expression of a mood and an attitude.” What’s this year’s? “Greenery, a refreshing and revitalizing shade symbolic of new beginnings.” Sounds pretty bang on then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the omnipresent pineapple of a year or two ago? It has been replaced this year with yet more greenery in the form of cacti. Healy believes these “novelty objects” are a reflection of the transient way many of us live nowadays. She advises retailers to stock up on small, quirky objects that make people feel happy - and which they can easily move house with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you’re renting you might not be able to change the decor and you might not have much room, but you can include a bit of fun in your interior. Something that boosts your mood and that you can take with you when you leave,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To offset the predominance of greenery there will be plenty of florals in 2017. Think dusky Oriental flowers or “acid tropic” colours, birds of paradise and animals. Perhaps flamingos will be the new pineapple?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Inspiration" /><summary type="html">Research interiors trends for 2017 and you’ll come up with a heady mix of foliage, natural raw materials, visceral texture and an abundance of colour.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trendspotting: How to buy homeware and gifts that will fly off the shelves</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trendspotting: How to buy homeware and gifts that will fly off the shelves" /><published>2017-04-13T05:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T05:19:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves/">&lt;p&gt;You’ve got the shop looking great and you know what your consumers like. But you want to make sure your stock is making the most out of the zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: how do you judge what to buy without making a mistake? The conundrum of whether to follow trends, or to simply stick with what’s safe, is as old as the hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some top tips for buying with the times in a way that won’t leave you with gimmicky pieces you’re unable to shift in six months’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHY DO THINGS GET TRENDY?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason that trends emerge when they do. It isn’t just that all of a sudden everyone loves hot pink. The strings of politics, the economy, the news and other social factors converge and influence us. Identifying what these different mechanisms are is half the battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When we think of trends we think of bloggers wearing a new style. But we need to look a bit higher than that. At politics, environmental factors, human rights, gender stereotyping,” says trend consultant Louise Healy. “OK, that might sound quite broad. But if you think about the things that are important to people now, you can work out what they might need.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what kinds of issues are being talked about in the pub, the supermarket, by your mum, your pals and see where the topics overlap - and how you, as a retailer, can respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, not gender-stereotyping too early is a buzz topic and you can see this in the colours that are now being recommended by retailers for nursery furniture or walls. People don’t just want pink for girls and blue for boys any more, so the shops are responding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way we live also impacts hugely on what we buy. Generation Rent means plenty of people interested in buying homeware are actually unable to decorate their own homes or need to be able to pack up and easily move house with anything they use to dress up their apartments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because there has been a rise in the transience of the way we live people are keen on buying novelty objects that make us feel happy,” says Healy. Hence the proliferance of gold pineapples and cactus prints of the last couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLANNING FOR BESTSELLERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People buy when they have an emotional response. It isn’t just “Oh that would look excellent in my living room”, although that happens, admittedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can provide products with real provenance (i.e where/how they were made), display or tell consumers about any stories associated with them, or give a sense of how ethical, rare or intriguing it is, then you’re onto a winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are moving as a society towards buying things with heritage. That’s how you get people to engage emotionally. People buy things that mean something to them,” says Healy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also help with PR coverage. If you have sourced a product that is newsworthy or surprising then you might be able to interest a newspaper, magazine or blog in featuring it.
Consider products at each end of the scale: the lower cost, smaller items that are easier to shift; and the higher end, quality products that you don’t want to over-buy. If you’re new to trend-hunting then try some low value stuff to start with. But don’t be afraid to get bolder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SCOURING THE NET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way of buying wisely is to be as informed as possible. It might sound obvious but if you can be all over social media, checking out Twitter, Instagram, Pinterest and Facebook, for what’s going on in the industry, the styles, patterns and tropes that are the most hash-tagged, then it’s going to give you an edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be mindful particularly of how trends travel by following overseas social networks. Japan and the USA are particularly good indicators of trends that will travel to the UK and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also key sites you can follow regularly that do this and tend to aggregate insights into interesting analytical chunks. You don’t have to fork out loads for trend forecasting subscription services, either. Most of the biggest names in the industry have freely available blogs, such as WGSN’s Lifestyle &amp;amp; Interiors section, here (&lt;a href=&quot;http://https://www.wgsn.com/blogs/lifestyle/lifestyle-interiors/&quot;&gt;https://www.wgsn.com/blogs/lifestyle/lifestyle-interiors/&lt;/a&gt;); or LSN Global’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsnglobal.com/tag/Blog&quot;&gt;https://www.lsnglobal.com/tag/Blog&lt;/a&gt;). You don’t have to buy all the Trend Bible reports, you can follow the website (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trendbible.com&quot;&gt;https://www.trendbible.com&lt;/a&gt;) which is full of useful articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be a blog lover: try Abigail Ahern’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://abigailahern.com&quot;&gt;https://abigailahern.com&lt;/a&gt;) for seeing what the trendier, affluent section of urban design-enthusiasts are looking for. While Savvy Home blog is an inspiring, insight into what’s hot in interiors in the Antipodes (&lt;a href=&quot;http://savvyhomeblog.com&quot;&gt;http://savvyhomeblog.com&lt;/a&gt;). Cassandra LaValle’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cocokelley.com&quot;&gt;http://www.cocokelley.com&lt;/a&gt;) is the site to visit for uber luxury and boutique trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE INDUSTRY TALKS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another top tip is to follow what’s going on at trade shows on social media. You might not have made it to Paris or London’s Olympia but you can see the pictures and get some idea of the buzz-worthy topics that emerged from the big shows like Spring Fair and Premier Vision. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.springfair.com/&quot;&gt;Spring Fair&lt;/a&gt; (Gift and Home) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.purelondon.com/&quot;&gt;Pure London&lt;/a&gt; (Fashion) have free trend presentations at the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it’s worth following both trade shows via their websites eg. Premiere Vision’s spotlight on section (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.premierevision.com/en/categories/spotlight-on/&quot;&gt;http://www.premierevision.com/en/categories/spotlight-on/&lt;/a&gt;), for an idea of the biggest areas for trendhunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big brands such as Ikea and Farrow and Ball publish insights each season revealing the colours and trends they’re expecting to make a splash. Pantone publishes both a colour of the year and colours for each season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep on top of these, borrow ideas, take what you like and think laterally. If cherry red furniture is everywhere, buy some smaller domestic items in a similarly arresting ruby lacquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AVOIDING A TURKEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing when a trend is so over is as important as identifying one that is on the horizon. Remember those gold pineapples? They’re so 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year there are a number of interesting trends on the horizon but not all of them will work for the mainstream consumer. Acid tropic colour palettes may be great for the trade shows and smaller objects, but be wary of larger pieces or anything so zingy it requires sunglasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If in doubt ask about. Get feedback from your friends, consumers, use social media yourself to try stuff out and gauge a response. Be confident but develop an eye for good design and good quality - without either of those things even the most zeitgeisty product will flop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RULE OF THUMB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You need to really like what you buy. Don’t buy something you don’t like just because you think people will want it. Be objective but also be passionate about what you sell,” says Healy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Inspiration" /><summary type="html">You’ve got the shop looking great and you know what your consumers like. But you want to make sure your stock is making the most out of the zeitgeist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From bricks and mortar to online shop: How to branch out</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From bricks and mortar to online shop: How to branch out" /><published>2017-04-13T04:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T04:15:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out/">&lt;p&gt;There are lots of good reasons to branch out into selling online when you have an established shop – from growing your customer base to building brand loyalty. But running a successful store is no guarantee that online sales will follow. So how can you get the move from bricks and mortar to virtual store right? Follow these steps from retailers who’ve already been there and bought the t-shirt. (They ordered it online…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Do your research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rule of starting any enterprise is size-up your market – and one obvious advantage of having a physical shop is that you’ve got customers you can canvas for opinion. Ask if they’d buy online from you if they had the option. The answers should yield some valuable – and possibly surprising – market data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracey McAllister runs Home Made Beautiful (&lt;a href=&quot;http://homemadebeautifulni.com/&quot;&gt;homemadebeautifulni.com&lt;/a&gt;) and is launching an online shop too. “We get lots of tourists and seasonal visitors (as opposed to locals) coming to the shop who often express a desire to buy more than their luggage restrictions allow,” she says. “We offer to ship their purchase home but quite often they ask for details of items so they can find them online later – if we can direct them to our own online store then we aren’t losing out on these sales, and we’re creating potential cross selling / up-selling opportunities too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Have a separate strategy for your online and offline sales&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a mistake to view an online store as a bolt-on to your physical shop. “There will be many crossovers between your online and offline sales but you need to think of each independently so that you can cater to both markets and their customers accordingly,” says Lisa Forde, who for the past 14 years has run The Card Gallery (&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecardgallery.co.uk&quot;&gt;thecardgallery.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;) and has two online stores (&lt;a href=&quot;http://treeofhearts.co.uk&quot;&gt;treeofhearts.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Make yourself easy to find&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s vital to determine why you’re different from other online shops, and spell out what you offer that larger online retailers don’t. Are your products sustainable / locally-made / eco-friendly / unique / handmade / of distinctive quality? Familiarise yourself with SEO best practice (or hire an expert) to ensure people searching for those products can find you easily. Lisa Forde adds: “You may also want to advertise online, build up your rankings so customers can find you on Google, and use social media to build awareness.”(there are a lot of free seminars on these topics at Spring Fair, Autumn Fair and Pure London trade shows, check out the Events page for more info)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Think about the whole package – literally&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of treating packaging as an afterthought, and never cut costs here. “Packaging adds cost to your product but it needs to be adequate to ensure your customer’s orders always arrive in tip-top condition,” says Lisa. “The company who delivers your products will form part of the service you offer too, so be sure they won’t disappoint your customers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Part of the consumer experience is the opening of the parcel,” adds Clare Bennett Smith, co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://curry-with-love.co.uk&quot;&gt;curry-with-love.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;. “It’s worth putting your logo on the parcel too – a bit of extra marketing can’t hurt! And I always put a handwritten note in with our orders, thanking the customer by name. Little things like that help build brand loyalty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Signed, sealed… delivered?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Think about the type of products you sell and the best delivery methods for them – are your goods perishable, breakable, easily damaged, very large or very small?” says Lisa. “There are lots of postage and courier options plus fast and slower delivery options so think about the best ones to suit your products – but be mindful that customers want their orders quickly, whichever market you are in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lots of companies, including Royal Mail, offer a pick-up service,” adds Bennett Smith. “Also think about the cost of the item being posted. If it’s of high value or bespoke, it’s advisable to use a courier who will track the item, giving both seller and customer peace of mind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Consider free delivery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a relatively low-cost product, it could be worthwhile offering free P&amp;amp;P within the UK. “If someone’s paying £3.75 for a curry kit, we felt they wouldn’t want to pay an extra £3.30 to cover postage,” explains Bennett Smith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our kits are light and flat so we can post up to three kits out at a time as a large letter. Anything over that goes as a small parcel and costs us £3.12. We’ve always used Royal Mail and in the main, they provide a good service.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, postage is one of the company’s biggest overheads so Bennet Smith recommends investing in a franking machine – she projects theirs will save the business around £1500 per annum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t pile products up in boxes and expect customers to imagine how they look and feel in-store, so don’t do the equivalent online – your imagery is what your customers will base buying decisions on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Original imagery of our products helps differentiate us from many of the other online stores in our niche who simply use stock images or photos from suppliers,” says Sam Williamson (&lt;a href=&quot;http://ahume.co.uk&quot;&gt;ahume.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;). “We also fill our About pages and our blog with as much personality, original imagery and expertise as possible, which means our website reflects the aesthetic of our shops.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Go live!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, go live on your transactional website only when everything else is truly complete. It only takes a few ‘teething problems’ – and the associated negative reviews – to create problems, so don’t rush this final stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t make the mistake of thinking the hard work is over once your site goes live, adds Fiona Kennedy &lt;a href=&quot;http://redrubyrouge.com&quot;&gt;redrubyrouge.com&lt;/a&gt;. “Think ahead to how you plan to keep on top of stock,” she says. “Bringing customers to your site to shop is one hurdle but if they click through to buy items that are in fact unavailable, your job is much more difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However long you think you’ll need to spend in preparation before you launch your online shop, double it. It’s better to end up ready earlier than anticipated than the other way round. “The designer who created my site could have done it in two weeks theoretically but when you factor in how much more work there is involved than you think, it’s better to allow more like 6-12 months,” says Tracey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no such thing as a ball-park figure for what it will cost to take your business online because the variables are endless but when working out your budget remember that what you outsource to an expert will save you time – and you can’t put a price on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beautiful website that works seamlessly is critical to your success – it’s a false economy to scrimp on this. “We all know retailers whose shops are beautiful but whose sites let them down,” says Tracey. “Ultimately, when people land on my page I want them to feel the same ‘wow factor’ they have when they set foot through the door,” she says. “Otherwise we’re selling ourselves short.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ecommerce" /><summary type="html">There are lots of good reasons to branch out into selling online when you have an established shop – from growing your customer base to building brand loyalty. But running a successful store is no guarantee that online sales will follow. So how can you get the move from bricks and mortar to virtual store right? Follow these steps from retailers who’ve already been there and bought the t-shirt. (They ordered it online…)</summary></entry></feed>