<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://insideretail.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://insideretail.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-05-19T14:37:54+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/</id><title type="html">Inside Retail</title><subtitle>The online destination for independent retailers. Whether you sell on the high street or online, are just getting started or tweaking the dream, you can find stories, tips, interviews and inspiration to help accelerate the growth of your business.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What Do Big Retailers Fear? You!</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Do Big Retailers Fear? You!" /><published>2017-05-05T12:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-05-05T12:38:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/whats-do-big-retailers-fear-you/">&lt;p&gt;This month I visited the World Retail Congress in Dubai, to see what the world’s leading retailers are up to, and how they feel about their own progress in giving modern customers what they want. I went because although the growth strategy for Calvin Klein is a long way from that of my local independent boutique in Oxfordshire, I wanted to see what we, in the Independent Retail community could learn from the biggest and best. I also suspected there might be opportunities discussed that smaller retailers are best placed to take advantage of, and I wasn’t wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away really excited despite the fact that brands like Macy’s, Marks and Spencer and lots of the other retailers present, are having a nightmare keeping up with customers changing demands. My unseemly optimism was down to things I heard constantly repeated during the event: The key to sustainable retail is catering to young consumers who want:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An experience. Might be emotional, might be entertaining, but not just ‘stuff’, it might even be that your products deliver this by having a story of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A sense of place, a local connection. A shop that’s a part of a community, perhaps with products that are linked to the area, perhaps an online shop with a strong regional personality&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A personal service. People who say hello, emails that tell your best customers when they’re favourite soap has been delivered, packaging that says thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huge stores like Waterstones are opening pretend independent shops to imitate those things and all progressive multinational retailers are spending huge sums on their customer data, so that they can create the impression of personal engagement. Actual indies have this already, and this presents  a huge opportunity to make the most of what comes naturally to them and use it to become a destination in their area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waterstones actually had a great year, despite Amazon’s total domination of the book market, by using their experience and book recommendations to stand out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inspiration from larger retailers on elements you might want to adapt for your own store, follow the advice of Martin Newman Founder of famous consultancy Practicology, and check out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pages.rapha.cc/clubs&quot;&gt;Rapha&lt;/a&gt;. The cycle retailer has styled its stores a club houses and offers an amazing array of events, a real sense of community. Revenues areup 30% on the previous 12 months, so what they’re doing is obviously working.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jo Malone’s new store, Jo Loves. 92% of people who took part in her Perfume Painting experience went on to make a purchase. Take a look at her &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.joloves.com/experiences&quot;&gt;new initiatives&lt;/a&gt; for inspiration on making your store an unexpected delight for customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the ability to change direction and respond to the customer, at speeds that large retailers can only dream of, indies are perfectly placed to offer the kind of retail experience consumers want. I know it’s very difficult to take time away from the day to day management to look at how to develop your store, or in the words of Exec Director of M&amp;amp;S Patrick Bousquet-Chavanne, answer the question, “What do you want to be when you grow up”;. But the rapid changes in the industry have created an opportunity, and it’s important to take it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve picked out five of the most important quotes I heard during the congress. I hope you find them useful. If you’d like us to follow up on any of these topics to get more detail for you, email me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“A customer who engages with us on more than one platform is 5 times more valuable to us than one who only engages with us on one” Terry Lundgren, Chairman, Macy’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that if one of your customers likes your Facebook post and buys then something from you in-store for instance, that person is much more likely to buy from you again, and to spend more than if they’d only popped into the shop. You could use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pinterest, Facebook, Instagram,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;An online store, a pop up shop,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A guest blog/ Q&amp;amp;A on a local publication,&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Events in your garden centre&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sponsorship of your local football team.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are loads of different ways to give your potential customers an opportunity to build trust in and interest in your shop. None of which require a Macy’s budget and 728 stores!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“When we opened Bloomingdales in Kuwait we made it a women-only store. This was controversial and took a lot of convincing the board but it’s highly successful. Don’t be afraid to take a risk if you know what your customers want” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessoffashion.com/community/people/khalid-al-tayer&quot;&gt;Khalid Al Tayer, CEO, Al Tayer Insignia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re probably not expanding to Kuwait but the willingness to listen to local customers made Bloomingdales a lot of money, so there’s no reason it can’t do the same for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to open a second store don’t just reproduce your product range and call it a day. Conduct local research to see if incomes, tastes, age groups etc are different. Invite yourself to local community groups – golf, mums and toddlers, WI, swing dancing and ask them what they would like to be able to buy from you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you’re sure, take a risk, whether in a new store or the existing one. If you know from your research and experience that your customers want a range of socks with flamingos, don’t buy black tights instead just to be safe, they can buy those anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tell your customers about what you’ve done for them. If you’ve opened a new shop, or taken another risk, GO BIG in telling people about it. Why you did it, how excited you are, where to buy and how, and make sure you’ve got it online! It’s where people look for new things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“83% of customers want a personalised experience” Brian Elliot, Managing Partner, McKinsey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McKinsey advise huge corporations on how to transform their businesses and Brian talked a lot about using big data to give a personal experience. The end game is a series of actions based on using customer information, to make more money for the retailers. Some key tricks the big boys use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Using personalisation to shift old stock. Offer customers who have purchased a product before, a small discount before it goes on sale. Ie: ‘Mrs Jones, you bought a Cath Kidstone gardening fork from us in June. We’d like to offer you a 10% discount on the rest of the range, to give you first choice before it goes on sale’. This can help you get better margins on products prior to heavier discounting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tell people who tried to buy something, when it’s back in stock.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Send people relevant content. For instance, a tip sheet you’ve written on how to style a jumpsuit for a wedding, sent to women in their 30s. Or chatting to people in-store, about the occasion they’re buying for, and making suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these work best if you have your customers email addresses or home addresses. If you don’t have those, it might be time to start thinking about how to collect them. Don’t forget though, the reason big retail focusses on email is because they cannot realistically offer a personal service instore (with new interactive changing rooms, this is just around the corner for the fashion industry). If you know your best customers by name, and/or have well trained staff, you can create a personal service, but without a system to record what your customer loves, it is difficult to keep track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“On Amazon, small no-name brands are the biggest competitors to brands like Sony and L’Oreal” Spencer Millerberg, Founder, One Click Retail.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon is a key reason for the decline of big retail and in the small retail community we need to recognise its influence without being intimidated. One Click Retail analyse product sales on Amazon. If you’re thinking about using Amazon for your own gain, here are some tips from a company that tracks how products perform on the platform. They advise companies like Unilever and Nestle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;90% of purchases begin with the search bar. Nobody chooses the ‘shop by department’ option&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;To take advantage of that, describe your product using words the customer will search for eg, Soap not ‘cleansing bar (a mistake Dove made!), and fish tank rather than an aquatic orb. Good search terms result in more people to your product page, it generates traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;95% of customers look at ALL the photos and these are the best way to convert the people who visit your product page, to paying customers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most customers don’t scroll down to the bottom of the product page, they just look at the top part ‘above the fold’ and all the pictures. Make sure the text and photos at the top of the listing are detailed and interesting enough that the customer can feel confident purchasing from you.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on these until you’ve managed to get onto the first page of the search results will put you in a position to compete on a level playing field with enormous conglomerates. And if you’re getting good reviews there’s no reason you can’t outsell Sony!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Department Store retail now makes up 2% of the total retail market. It used to be 10% and we’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.retail-week.com/sectors/home-and-diy/big-box-little-box-cardboard-box-why-big-retailers-are-shrinking/7011157.article&quot;&gt;seen 10yrs of steady decline&lt;/a&gt;.” Robin Lewis, CEO, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.therobinreport.com/&quot;&gt;The Robin Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big thing I took from this fascinating session was that ‘big stores are not cool’. As young consumers look to experience and discover things, driving to an out of town retail park and wandering around DFS doesn’t cut it. The Big Box formats are only surviving in the US (where they lead, we follow) if they operate like neighbourhoods, with sports, community, great food, farmers markets ie a Highstreet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robin said, ‘The Future of retail can be the highstreet, if it’s a good highstreet’, and he’s got a lot of data to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Independents have a better profit potential than Big Box retail. A single brand/store personality, and an intimate, social atmosphere is where the potential is. Ralph Lauren, Gap, Levi all missed the boat with this and got confusing and stale&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The small shop has better potential to offer generation Z customers want they want&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cause-based retailing really sells now, trust is important. Eg, selling a product that you know contributes to charity, or is made from waste plastic, or by disadvantaged people will appeal to young buyers. You can work with tiny, unique suppliers, big retailers cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sharing, renting and swapping are becoming very popular, small shops find it easier to offer this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bricks and mortar have the huge advantage of being able to offer an online and offline service, with customers who have access to multiple platforms spending 3,4,5 times more, this is a huge asset. Pure online retailers struggle to offer that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His parting shot. “The consumer has changed totally” Small start-ups are going to chip away at the big stores because they can’t move fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon is a big beast but it’s a great place for would be online-indie retailers to get started. Testing products, making sure you’re logistics and systems work etc, before you start to offer a full range under your own steam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Macy’s put it ‘Why would a 25 year old want to drive to an out of town store to look at a huge building filled with stuff, when they could buy it online and then go rock climbing. We need to provide an experience’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our independent shops can offer that experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get in touch with me if you’re doing a great job of making shopping fun. I’d love to interview you about what you’re up to.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="inspiration" /><summary type="html">This month I visited the World Retail Congress in Dubai, to see what the world’s leading retailers are up to, and how they feel about their own progress in giving modern customers what they want. I went because although the growth strategy for Calvin Klein is a long way from that of my local independent boutique in Oxfordshire, I wanted to see what we, in the Independent Retail community could learn from the biggest and best. I also suspected there might be opportunities discussed that smaller retailers are best placed to take advantage of, and I wasn’t wrong.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch: Learn How Independent Menswear Retailer, Number Six, Uses Customer Data</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch: Learn How Independent Menswear Retailer, Number Six, Uses Customer Data" /><published>2017-04-27T15:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-27T15:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-customer-insight-at-number-six/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;win-with-vend&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;WIN WITH VEND:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-here-for-your-chance-to-win-20000-worth-of-retail-technology-support-and-marketing-all-thanks-to-vend&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;Enter here for your chance to WIN £20,000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; worth of retail technology, support, and marketing all thanks to Vend.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-personal-connection-with-customers&quot;&gt;A personal connection with customers:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent retailers have always prided themselves on being close to their customers and with simple technology its possible to give your valued customers the inside scoop on new deliveries of their favourite products, personalised discounts and anything else you’d like to tell them. Everyone from John Lewis to Number Six, the indie retailer interviewed here, see immediate boosts in sales after communicating with customers so it’s well worth the effort!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting data and being able to crunch the sales numbers using data analytics has very much been the domain of larger organisations, but as these activities become essential for smaller retailers as well, new technology companies have risen to the challenge of creating great products for them. We feature Vend in this video and they’re a prime example of that trend. Their ePOS system means it is now possible for smaller retailers to cost effectively offer your customers the same service they get from the biggest names in retail, but with all the added benefits of shopping with a small independent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-for-solutions-to-help-drive-your-business-forward&quot;&gt;Looking for solutions to help drive your business forward?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jake Hardy, owner of successful menswear retailer, Number Six, shares how he easily gathers and uses customer information to offer them exactly what they’ve asked for. He shares ideas on what to send and when, to get the best up-tick in sales whilst being useful and  appealing to customers, rather than an inbox irritant. Interviewed by Sophy Searight, Editor at Inside Retail, in partnership with Vend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inside Retail are proud to have Vend on board as a partner, we share the same ambitions for a thriving high street.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vendhq.com/uk/london?campaign=7016F000001AWsi&amp;amp;utm_source=insideretail&amp;amp;utm_medium=promotion&amp;amp;utm_campaign=retail_growth&quot;&gt;Enter to win&lt;/a&gt; and grow your retail with Vend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">WIN WITH VEND:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interiors trends for 2017 and how to style your store to increase footfall</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interiors trends for 2017 and how to style your store to increase footfall" /><published>2017-04-13T06:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T06:19:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/interiors-trends-for-2017-and-how-to-style-your-store-to-increase-footfall/">&lt;p&gt;Research interiors trends for 2017 and you’ll come up with a heady mix of foliage, natural raw materials, visceral texture and an abundance of colour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounds fantastic for spring. But, if I’m a retailer hoping to stock up on items that will appeal to consumers throughout the year, how is this stuff going to age?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of an independent retailer’s job is identifying the trends that are going to have long legs - and the ones to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Lisa White, head of Lifestyle &amp;amp; Interiors at WGSN, a safe option is to stick to plant life - which can bring both seasonal flair to your shop and opportunities for buyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Indoor plants are trending tremendously at the moment,” says White. She suspects that this will run and run and so advises to get potting up for both summer and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In the autumn consumers like to take a bit of nature back inside with them—so this will be a good time to stock up on plant accessories,” she says. “The indoor garden is getting more glamorous and people are willing to spend a bit more money on plant accessories, for themselves and also for gifts. Think beautiful pots in interesting materials, from artisanal ceramics to brushed brass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GOING TO POT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Plant stands will also be trending - so people can put their plants on a pedestal. There will also be a continuation of hanging plants in macramé planters, but this autumn and winter they will be in more sophisticated materials and colours to bring a bit of glam to the home garden.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plants are also a great way to make your shop appear fresh. Move them about, put them in big, colourful pots and it could really increase footfall as we move from the heat of summer towards winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Bring in some easy-care plants into the store to add freshness and personality,” says White. “Cacti have been popular, but if you want something different, 1970s plants will be trending [by the autumn], and they are very easy to care for: spider plants, rubber plants, pileas. You’ll find people linger longer in retail spaces that have greenery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know how to identify the key trend of the year? “It’s really useful to look at Pantone’s colour of the year. It’s starting to not just be a colour predictor but a social indicator as well,” says trend consultant Louise Healy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pantone describes its annual selection as “a colour snapshot of what we see taking place in our global culture that serves as an expression of a mood and an attitude.” What’s this year’s? “Greenery, a refreshing and revitalizing shade symbolic of new beginnings.” Sounds pretty bang on then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the omnipresent pineapple of a year or two ago? It has been replaced this year with yet more greenery in the form of cacti. Healy believes these “novelty objects” are a reflection of the transient way many of us live nowadays. She advises retailers to stock up on small, quirky objects that make people feel happy - and which they can easily move house with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you’re renting you might not be able to change the decor and you might not have much room, but you can include a bit of fun in your interior. Something that boosts your mood and that you can take with you when you leave,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To offset the predominance of greenery there will be plenty of florals in 2017. Think dusky Oriental flowers or “acid tropic” colours, birds of paradise and animals. Perhaps flamingos will be the new pineapple?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Inspiration" /><summary type="html">Research interiors trends for 2017 and you’ll come up with a heady mix of foliage, natural raw materials, visceral texture and an abundance of colour.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trendspotting: How to buy homeware and gifts that will fly off the shelves</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trendspotting: How to buy homeware and gifts that will fly off the shelves" /><published>2017-04-13T05:19:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T05:19:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/trendspotting-how-to-buy-homeware-and-gifts-that-will-fly-off-the-shelves/">&lt;p&gt;You’ve got the shop looking great and you know what your consumers like. But you want to make sure your stock is making the most out of the zeitgeist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: how do you judge what to buy without making a mistake? The conundrum of whether to follow trends, or to simply stick with what’s safe, is as old as the hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some top tips for buying with the times in a way that won’t leave you with gimmicky pieces you’re unable to shift in six months’ time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHY DO THINGS GET TRENDY?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a reason that trends emerge when they do. It isn’t just that all of a sudden everyone loves hot pink. The strings of politics, the economy, the news and other social factors converge and influence us. Identifying what these different mechanisms are is half the battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When we think of trends we think of bloggers wearing a new style. But we need to look a bit higher than that. At politics, environmental factors, human rights, gender stereotyping,” says trend consultant Louise Healy. “OK, that might sound quite broad. But if you think about the things that are important to people now, you can work out what they might need.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about what kinds of issues are being talked about in the pub, the supermarket, by your mum, your pals and see where the topics overlap - and how you, as a retailer, can respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, not gender-stereotyping too early is a buzz topic and you can see this in the colours that are now being recommended by retailers for nursery furniture or walls. People don’t just want pink for girls and blue for boys any more, so the shops are responding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way we live also impacts hugely on what we buy. Generation Rent means plenty of people interested in buying homeware are actually unable to decorate their own homes or need to be able to pack up and easily move house with anything they use to dress up their apartments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because there has been a rise in the transience of the way we live people are keen on buying novelty objects that make us feel happy,” says Healy. Hence the proliferance of gold pineapples and cactus prints of the last couple of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLANNING FOR BESTSELLERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People buy when they have an emotional response. It isn’t just “Oh that would look excellent in my living room”, although that happens, admittedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can provide products with real provenance (i.e where/how they were made), display or tell consumers about any stories associated with them, or give a sense of how ethical, rare or intriguing it is, then you’re onto a winner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are moving as a society towards buying things with heritage. That’s how you get people to engage emotionally. People buy things that mean something to them,” says Healy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can also help with PR coverage. If you have sourced a product that is newsworthy or surprising then you might be able to interest a newspaper, magazine or blog in featuring it.
Consider products at each end of the scale: the lower cost, smaller items that are easier to shift; and the higher end, quality products that you don’t want to over-buy. If you’re new to trend-hunting then try some low value stuff to start with. But don’t be afraid to get bolder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SCOURING THE NET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way of buying wisely is to be as informed as possible. It might sound obvious but if you can be all over social media, checking out Twitter, Instagram, Pinterest and Facebook, for what’s going on in the industry, the styles, patterns and tropes that are the most hash-tagged, then it’s going to give you an edge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be mindful particularly of how trends travel by following overseas social networks. Japan and the USA are particularly good indicators of trends that will travel to the UK and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also key sites you can follow regularly that do this and tend to aggregate insights into interesting analytical chunks. You don’t have to fork out loads for trend forecasting subscription services, either. Most of the biggest names in the industry have freely available blogs, such as WGSN’s Lifestyle &amp;amp; Interiors section, here (&lt;a href=&quot;http://https://www.wgsn.com/blogs/lifestyle/lifestyle-interiors/&quot;&gt;https://www.wgsn.com/blogs/lifestyle/lifestyle-interiors/&lt;/a&gt;); or LSN Global’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lsnglobal.com/tag/Blog&quot;&gt;https://www.lsnglobal.com/tag/Blog&lt;/a&gt;). You don’t have to buy all the Trend Bible reports, you can follow the website (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trendbible.com&quot;&gt;https://www.trendbible.com&lt;/a&gt;) which is full of useful articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be a blog lover: try Abigail Ahern’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://abigailahern.com&quot;&gt;https://abigailahern.com&lt;/a&gt;) for seeing what the trendier, affluent section of urban design-enthusiasts are looking for. While Savvy Home blog is an inspiring, insight into what’s hot in interiors in the Antipodes (&lt;a href=&quot;http://savvyhomeblog.com&quot;&gt;http://savvyhomeblog.com&lt;/a&gt;). Cassandra LaValle’s blog (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cocokelley.com&quot;&gt;http://www.cocokelley.com&lt;/a&gt;) is the site to visit for uber luxury and boutique trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE INDUSTRY TALKS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another top tip is to follow what’s going on at trade shows on social media. You might not have made it to Paris or London’s Olympia but you can see the pictures and get some idea of the buzz-worthy topics that emerged from the big shows like Spring Fair and Premier Vision. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.springfair.com/&quot;&gt;Spring Fair&lt;/a&gt; (Gift and Home) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.purelondon.com/&quot;&gt;Pure London&lt;/a&gt; (Fashion) have free trend presentations at the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it’s worth following both trade shows via their websites eg. Premiere Vision’s spotlight on section (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.premierevision.com/en/categories/spotlight-on/&quot;&gt;http://www.premierevision.com/en/categories/spotlight-on/&lt;/a&gt;), for an idea of the biggest areas for trendhunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big brands such as Ikea and Farrow and Ball publish insights each season revealing the colours and trends they’re expecting to make a splash. Pantone publishes both a colour of the year and colours for each season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep on top of these, borrow ideas, take what you like and think laterally. If cherry red furniture is everywhere, buy some smaller domestic items in a similarly arresting ruby lacquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AVOIDING A TURKEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing when a trend is so over is as important as identifying one that is on the horizon. Remember those gold pineapples? They’re so 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year there are a number of interesting trends on the horizon but not all of them will work for the mainstream consumer. Acid tropic colour palettes may be great for the trade shows and smaller objects, but be wary of larger pieces or anything so zingy it requires sunglasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If in doubt ask about. Get feedback from your friends, consumers, use social media yourself to try stuff out and gauge a response. Be confident but develop an eye for good design and good quality - without either of those things even the most zeitgeisty product will flop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RULE OF THUMB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You need to really like what you buy. Don’t buy something you don’t like just because you think people will want it. Be objective but also be passionate about what you sell,” says Healy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Inspiration" /><summary type="html">You’ve got the shop looking great and you know what your consumers like. But you want to make sure your stock is making the most out of the zeitgeist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From bricks and mortar to online shop: How to branch out</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From bricks and mortar to online shop: How to branch out" /><published>2017-04-13T04:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-04-13T04:15:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/from-bricks-and-mortar-to-virtual-shop-how-to-branch-out/">&lt;p&gt;There are lots of good reasons to branch out into selling online when you have an established shop – from growing your customer base to building brand loyalty. But running a successful store is no guarantee that online sales will follow. So how can you get the move from bricks and mortar to virtual store right? Follow these steps from retailers who’ve already been there and bought the t-shirt. (They ordered it online…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Do your research&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rule of starting any enterprise is size-up your market – and one obvious advantage of having a physical shop is that you’ve got customers you can canvas for opinion. Ask if they’d buy online from you if they had the option. The answers should yield some valuable – and possibly surprising – market data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracey McAllister runs Home Made Beautiful (&lt;a href=&quot;http://homemadebeautifulni.com/&quot;&gt;homemadebeautifulni.com&lt;/a&gt;) and is launching an online shop too. “We get lots of tourists and seasonal visitors (as opposed to locals) coming to the shop who often express a desire to buy more than their luggage restrictions allow,” she says. “We offer to ship their purchase home but quite often they ask for details of items so they can find them online later – if we can direct them to our own online store then we aren’t losing out on these sales, and we’re creating potential cross selling / up-selling opportunities too.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Have a separate strategy for your online and offline sales&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a mistake to view an online store as a bolt-on to your physical shop. “There will be many crossovers between your online and offline sales but you need to think of each independently so that you can cater to both markets and their customers accordingly,” says Lisa Forde, who for the past 14 years has run The Card Gallery (&lt;a href=&quot;http://thecardgallery.co.uk&quot;&gt;thecardgallery.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;) and has two online stores (&lt;a href=&quot;http://treeofhearts.co.uk&quot;&gt;treeofhearts.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Make yourself easy to find&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s vital to determine why you’re different from other online shops, and spell out what you offer that larger online retailers don’t. Are your products sustainable / locally-made / eco-friendly / unique / handmade / of distinctive quality? Familiarise yourself with SEO best practice (or hire an expert) to ensure people searching for those products can find you easily. Lisa Forde adds: “You may also want to advertise online, build up your rankings so customers can find you on Google, and use social media to build awareness.”(there are a lot of free seminars on these topics at Spring Fair, Autumn Fair and Pure London trade shows, check out the Events page for more info)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Think about the whole package – literally&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of treating packaging as an afterthought, and never cut costs here. “Packaging adds cost to your product but it needs to be adequate to ensure your customer’s orders always arrive in tip-top condition,” says Lisa. “The company who delivers your products will form part of the service you offer too, so be sure they won’t disappoint your customers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Part of the consumer experience is the opening of the parcel,” adds Clare Bennett Smith, co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://curry-with-love.co.uk&quot;&gt;curry-with-love.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;. “It’s worth putting your logo on the parcel too – a bit of extra marketing can’t hurt! And I always put a handwritten note in with our orders, thanking the customer by name. Little things like that help build brand loyalty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Signed, sealed… delivered?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Think about the type of products you sell and the best delivery methods for them – are your goods perishable, breakable, easily damaged, very large or very small?” says Lisa. “There are lots of postage and courier options plus fast and slower delivery options so think about the best ones to suit your products – but be mindful that customers want their orders quickly, whichever market you are in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Lots of companies, including Royal Mail, offer a pick-up service,” adds Bennett Smith. “Also think about the cost of the item being posted. If it’s of high value or bespoke, it’s advisable to use a courier who will track the item, giving both seller and customer peace of mind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Consider free delivery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a relatively low-cost product, it could be worthwhile offering free P&amp;amp;P within the UK. “If someone’s paying £3.75 for a curry kit, we felt they wouldn’t want to pay an extra £3.30 to cover postage,” explains Bennett Smith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our kits are light and flat so we can post up to three kits out at a time as a large letter. Anything over that goes as a small parcel and costs us £3.12. We’ve always used Royal Mail and in the main, they provide a good service.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, postage is one of the company’s biggest overheads so Bennet Smith recommends investing in a franking machine – she projects theirs will save the business around £1500 per annum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Images&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t pile products up in boxes and expect customers to imagine how they look and feel in-store, so don’t do the equivalent online – your imagery is what your customers will base buying decisions on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Original imagery of our products helps differentiate us from many of the other online stores in our niche who simply use stock images or photos from suppliers,” says Sam Williamson (&lt;a href=&quot;http://ahume.co.uk&quot;&gt;ahume.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;). “We also fill our About pages and our blog with as much personality, original imagery and expertise as possible, which means our website reflects the aesthetic of our shops.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Go live!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, go live on your transactional website only when everything else is truly complete. It only takes a few ‘teething problems’ – and the associated negative reviews – to create problems, so don’t rush this final stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don’t make the mistake of thinking the hard work is over once your site goes live, adds Fiona Kennedy &lt;a href=&quot;http://redrubyrouge.com&quot;&gt;redrubyrouge.com&lt;/a&gt;. “Think ahead to how you plan to keep on top of stock,” she says. “Bringing customers to your site to shop is one hurdle but if they click through to buy items that are in fact unavailable, your job is much more difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However long you think you’ll need to spend in preparation before you launch your online shop, double it. It’s better to end up ready earlier than anticipated than the other way round. “The designer who created my site could have done it in two weeks theoretically but when you factor in how much more work there is involved than you think, it’s better to allow more like 6-12 months,” says Tracey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no such thing as a ball-park figure for what it will cost to take your business online because the variables are endless but when working out your budget remember that what you outsource to an expert will save you time – and you can’t put a price on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beautiful website that works seamlessly is critical to your success – it’s a false economy to scrimp on this. “We all know retailers whose shops are beautiful but whose sites let them down,” says Tracey. “Ultimately, when people land on my page I want them to feel the same ‘wow factor’ they have when they set foot through the door,” she says. “Otherwise we’re selling ourselves short.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ecommerce" /><summary type="html">There are lots of good reasons to branch out into selling online when you have an established shop – from growing your customer base to building brand loyalty. But running a successful store is no guarantee that online sales will follow. So how can you get the move from bricks and mortar to virtual store right? Follow these steps from retailers who’ve already been there and bought the t-shirt. (They ordered it online…)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch: Create a buzz - Ecommerce on a shoestring budget</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/create-a-buzz-ecommerce-on-a-shoestring-budget/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch: Create a buzz - Ecommerce on a shoestring budget" /><published>2017-03-30T14:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-30T14:16:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/create-a-buzz-ecommerce-on-a-shoestring-budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/create-a-buzz-ecommerce-on-a-shoestring-budget/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/GT-Creating-a-Buzz-Video-Form.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/create-a-buzz-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;create-a-buzz-02.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here at Inside Retail, we know from our conversations with you in the independent retail community that actually generating a ‘buzz’ and a marketing message around your new online business can be very challenging, particularly because some of your big competitors, like Amazon for instance, have enormous budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;that-doesnt-need-to-stand-in-your-way-and-alasdair-talks-us-through-how-you-can-implement-some-simple-but-effective-online-marketing-tactics&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That doesn’t need to stand in your way, and Alasdair talks us through how you can implement some simple but effective online marketing tactics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch the tutorial and you’ll be taken through how to use Facebook to target your perfect customers, how you could use your website and social media to share customer experiences, creating a database and using that database to generate new customers while winning back old ones (with both email marketing and across social media), reaching out to social influencers (and using software to do this in the most effective way), as well as video and blog content creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside Retail has been working closely with G by Grant Thornton to develop The Retail Growth Programme. It’s designed specifically for independent retailers like you and as part of the programme, you’ll get to work with experts like Alasdair who will help you to plan and achieve future growth for both you and your business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is designed with the leader of retail businesses in mind; providing practical tools, plans and best practices that will help to facilitate rapid and sustainable business growth. During the year you will develop your knowledge in key areas to deliver your business goals: creating plans, networks and connections that will contribute to your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;g-helped-us-reconnect-with-our-purpose-and-strengths-as-well-as-realising-our-fuller-potential-with-regards-to-our-offering&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“G HELPED US RECONNECT WITH OUR PURPOSE AND STRENGTHS AS WELL AS REALISING OUR FULLER POTENTIAL WITH REGARDS TO OUR OFFERING.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asra Ali-Khan,
Managing Director, Liquid TV&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the G by Grant Thornton Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stand-out-from-the-crowd-and-achieve-rapid-and-sustainable-growth&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAND OUT FROM THE CROWD AND ACHIEVE RAPID AND SUSTAINABLE GROWTH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to learn, adopt new practices and develop personally are critical to business success. These newly adopted skills, applied to your business through clearly actionable plans, can set you apart in a crowded market, providing the catalyst for rapid and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme provides a unique opportunity for you to step back from the day-to-day demands of running your business, giving you the clarity and the time to develop a detailed, actionable plan for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the brochure with all the info here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/retail-growth-programme.pdf&quot; class=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Download Brochure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The benefits:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accelerated growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A robust and rigorous plan for growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More confidence and increased focus on priorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The path to improved profitability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More effective leadership and management skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drawing on the collective skills and knowledge of Grant Thornton’s extensive network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Retail Growth Programme is built around a series of growth workshops where you will develop and implement your growth strategy for your business. The programme is modular and allows you to continually apply your learning to how you run your business while you participate. The programme runs over 12 months. In between each workshop, you will continue working on developing and implementing your own growth strategy for your business, making immediate improvements every month.
Throughout the programme, you will be supported by an experienced account manager who works with you to ensure that you get the maximum value from your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who is it for?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambitious businesses in the retail sector&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it cost?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£5,000 + VAT (payable £1,250 + VAT per quarter)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does it take place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One monthly session in either London or Birmingham with support via phone and email across the duration of the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-12-month-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YOUR 12 MONTH PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH SUPPORT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic conversation and growth reviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dedicated account manager providing coaching and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly Peer Boards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly insights on key sectors and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH WORKSHOPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ten specially designed growth workshops for you to choose from a selection of sixteen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going International&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying and Merchandising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operations and Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customer and Sales Profiling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engaging and Retaining Talent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reaching the Market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing the Next Location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retail Space Design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulations and Legislation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financing Growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme is designed for retailers or those looking to diversify into the retail sector. If you are already successfully trading and now want to take the next step towards future growth then please get in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;click-here-to-find-out-more-about-the-g-by-grant-thornton-retail-growth-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the G by Grant Thornton Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online, no-one can see you’re small</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/online-no-one-can-see-youre-small/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online, no-one can see you’re small" /><published>2017-03-30T09:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-30T09:32:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/online-no-one-can-see-youre-small</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/online-no-one-can-see-youre-small/">&lt;p&gt;We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autumnfair.com/&quot;&gt;Autumn Fair&lt;/a&gt; (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to those who shared their views with us, I hope it’s useful. Look out for ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/think-small-think-added-value&quot;&gt;Think small, Think added value&lt;/a&gt;’, and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/battling-the-big-boys/&quot;&gt;Battling the big boys&lt;/a&gt;’ for more direct advice from your peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/editor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;editor.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about being online is that nobody can see you’re a small retailer. The bad thing is this means if you’re not as slick as John Lewis, they’ll think it’s your fault. We asked a panel of respondents how they worked against the big companies online and the answers were many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Older people, counterintuitively, weren’t intimidated by the Internet and nor were they afraid of the competition. Instead, and without infringing copyright(!), they ransacked the online giants for ideas on promotions, bundling, anything that might work for them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A number suggested that a website should be more than just the extension of a physical store. If you can offer only a basic transaction in which a customer buys your stock and Amazon can do it more cheaply, guess where the customer is going. If you offer advice and your own expertise, the giants can’t compete.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ignore “received wisdom”. Our responses suggested that social media may not be the best way to engage with customers searching on local directories like Scoop and Yelp. You’re likely to have finite amounts of time; make sure the information on those sites is up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Tools are available to you to keep your online offering constant. “It is surprising how many shops don’t know how to keep up to date with Google business so that people can easily find them,” said one respondent. “They want to see photos etc. This is the nut and bolt of things…”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you’re going to use social media or other platforms, have you checked where your customers hang out electronically? If you’re in a business to business environment they may be on LinkedIn rather than Facebook, for example. Ask them – then go where your market is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you employ younger staff who are on their smartphones the whole time? Or older, let’s not stereotype…anyway, they have digital skills. It might be worth establishing who can do what electronically and redeploying some of the skill sets already in your business. One respondent reported recruiting from universities purely to get at these skills, and it had paid handsomely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One respondent noted that it’s possible to get obsessed with statistics, and that someone will always find a stat that appears to apply to you (and which, we could add, will mysteriously make it plain that the person offering the stat has exactly the service to help). There is one stat that matters: after setting up your website or going online in another form, has your business increased?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Partnering with a blogger can be a good idea as long as you set a realistic objective. Electronic business because you think you ought to is a recipe for disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, watch out for the big lie about social media and other electronic marketing: the one that says it doesn’t cost anything. This is only true if you value your time and that of your staff at zero; assess the cost of building your business electronically, make sure you’ve set targets and milestones and you’ll have something to measure against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ecommerce" /><summary type="html">We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for Autumn Fair (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Think small, think added value</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/think-small-think-added-value/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Think small, think added value" /><published>2017-03-30T09:22:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-30T09:22:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/think-small-think-added-value</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/think-small-think-added-value/">&lt;p&gt;We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.autumnfair.com/&quot;&gt;Autumn Fair&lt;/a&gt; (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to those who shared their views with us, I hope it’s useful. Look out for ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/online-no-one-can-see-youre-small/&quot;&gt;Online, no one can see you’re small&lt;/a&gt;’, and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/battling-the-big-boys/&quot;&gt;Battling the big boys&lt;/a&gt;’ for more direct advice from your peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/editor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;editor.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of being a big retail chain or website like Amazon is that you have the logistics down pat – and that’s about it. Not that anyone should be less than respectful of the scale at which those companies operate, but it means that their business is purely transactional. The smaller organisation is therefore in a good position to add value, through personalisation, through quirkiness and a number of other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked a number of retailers how they go about adding value and therefore differentiating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Offer some old fashioned service. Are you a bookseller? Note what your regulars are enjoying reading, even offer them a book club if there are enough like minded people. Amazon and the online giants lack one thing: the ability to get people together. Make this one of your unique selling points.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Likewise people selling food and drink – tasting evenings, find out what your customers like and make them the odd recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Build in a “wow” factor, one respondent suggested. This needn’t be a massive event but it’s good to have some products that need to be handled and touched, like jewellery, or clothing that needs to be tried on. People don’t pass through the High Street as they used to, and don’t retailers know it – give them a reason to turn up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of our respondents said ”for the small independent retailers that are surviving and working, “they are working very hard to be successful – they are usually very active with event promotions in the local community.” This is unarguable – so how do you fit into your community? Are you a standalone shop, is there a noticeboard for community announcements?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A respondent visiting America noticed a number of stores with coffee tables or bars in the centre of the retail area. “This is the sort of experience that people need to be given in-store,” they said, although we’d urge caution; the cost structures including national living wage and business rates are not exactly the same in any two countries, so the fact that it works there may not translate seamlessly over here.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try to get some product exclusives so that people &lt;strong&gt;have&lt;/strong&gt; to come to you if they want them. The majors may come and take them off your hands eventually but by that time you’ll be onto another. Set aside some time to research what your customer actually wants and how to anticipate the next wave.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electronic world only amplifies what’s been going on in the High Street for some time; someone pioneers a product, it sells for a premium through a few specialists, it goes mainstream and everyone else picks it (or an equivalent) up, and at the end nobody can shift them. The online world accelerates the process but it hasn’t changed. By keeping in touch with the customer, by knowing what they want and forecasting what they’re going to want, you can become the business the giants follow rather than the one they stamp out because it’s doing the same as them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for Autumn Fair (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Battling the big boys</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/battling-the-big-boys/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Battling the big boys" /><published>2017-03-30T09:04:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-30T09:04:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/battling-the-big-boys</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/battling-the-big-boys/">&lt;p&gt;We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for Autumn Fair (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers.
\
Thank you to those who shared their views with us, I hope it’s useful. Look out for ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/online-no-one-can-see-youre-small/&quot;&gt;Online, no one can see you’re small&lt;/a&gt;’, and ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://insideretail.com/articles/think-small-think-added-value/&quot;&gt;Think small, Think added value&lt;/a&gt;’  for more direct advice from your peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sophy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/editor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;editor.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could be persuaded to panic. You’re a small retailer and your customer walks in holding a smartphone; you know they’re checking prices, you know they can serve themselves online without your help and you can’t throw the resources of one of the major High Street chains at the online world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that’s an issue for many smaller retailers because you’ve told us so. The average bricks and mortar retailer has seen trade falling by 2.4% a year in 2014 to 2.3% pa in 2015. The curious thing is that last year, 2016, retail sales rose by 2.1%, according to the Centre for Retail Research. And retail has always been competitive, hasn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s good news – it’s not just a case of “we’re doomed”. So what can a small retailer do about it? Respondents to our survey had a number of responses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only way the big companies can compete is on volume and logistics, so find another edge. Be the coolest, the most niche, take feedback from your customers and be seen to implement it. The bigger companies can’t react as quickly as you – it’s a strength, use it!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Try not to rely on a small group of customers from a particular demographic. Large retailers are redirecting footfall to the retail parks where they can. Use launches and promotional events to speak to and engage with your customer base – let them feel they’re buying from you rather than from a business.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get involved with the community. One of our respondents noted a local project called “Footfall”, which allowed independent retailers to hang kids’ work in empty shop windows. The supermarkets can be wise to this one too, but it can get proud parents coming back to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be proactive with your stock – is restocking the same thing over and over again the way to encourage new customers? If you’re a garden centre, once they’re used to buying product X they might resort to getting it delivered from an online source; considering why they like it and offering rotating, complementary products will keep them coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When it’s Christmas, offer mulled wine! Even teetotallers will welcome the smell of Christmas and visit your store rather than a soulless establishment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Never overlook the advantage you have of being in complete control. One of our respondents reported that customers found their wide and accessible aisles very appealing. If your larger competition’s selling point is in being an identikit branch, you can stymie them with this completely.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other thoughts on offer included growing your customer base even if you do perceive your premises as “small” – some loss of customers to the larger competition is inevitable, get a reputation for being the best place to go for service for a larger number and you can afford to take a small hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, consider something quirky and fun that works as an impulse buy. Those still happen in the bricks and mortar world more than they do online – just about nobody buys, for example, a greetings card online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can you offer something that just doesn’t fit into an online sale?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="in-store" /><summary type="html">We spoke to 40 small retailers as part of our research for Autumn Fair (trade show for retailers) about what their challenges and recommendations are for 2017. Here’s a bite-sized summary of how they’re approaching the challenge of pushing back against those online retailers. \ Thank you to those who shared their views with us, I hope it’s useful. Look out for ‘Online, no one can see you’re small’, and ‘Think small, Think added value’ for more direct advice from your peers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Watch: Creating A Brand &amp;amp; Personality For Your Shop</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-creating-a-brand-and-personality-for-your-shop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Watch: Creating A Brand &amp; Personality For Your Shop" /><published>2017-03-21T11:49:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-21T11:49:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-creating-a-brand-and-personality-for-your-shop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/watch-creating-a-brand-and-personality-for-your-shop/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/GT-Creating-a-brand.html&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/uploads/creating-a-brand.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;creating-a-brand.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lou Williams from &lt;a href=&quot;http://g.grantthornton.co.uk/explore/&quot;&gt;G by Grant Thornton &lt;/a&gt; talks to Inside Retail Editor, Sophy Searight about creating a brand &amp;amp; personality for your shop and the steps you can take to help build that successful personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lou is responsible for delivering the G Membership programme at Grant Thornton and as a part of this, has worked with Inside Retail to develop the Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed specifically for retailers, the Retail Growth Programme helps you plan and achieve the future growth ambitions you want for your business and for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is designed with the leader of retail businesses in mind; providing practical tools, plans and best practices that will help to facilitate rapid and sustainable business growth. During the year you will develop your knowledge in key areas to deliver your business goals: creating plans, networks and connections that will contribute to your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;g-helped-us-reconnect-with-our-purpose-and-strengths-as-well-as-realising-our-fuller-potential-with-regards-to-our-offering&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“G HELPED US RECONNECT WITH OUR PURPOSE AND STRENGTHS AS WELL AS REALISING OUR FULLER POTENTIAL WITH REGARDS TO OUR OFFERING.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asra Ali-Khan,
Managing Director, Liquid TV&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STAND OUT FROM THE CROWD AND ACHIEVE RAPID AND SUSTAINABLE GROWTH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to learn, adopt new practices and develop personally are critical to business success. These newly adopted skills, applied to your business through clearly actionable plans, can set you apart in a crowded market, providing the catalyst for rapid and sustainable growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme provides a unique opportunity for you to step back from the day-to-day demands of running your business, giving you the clarity and the time to develop a detailed, actionable plan for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download the brochure with all the info here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/uploads/Retail%20Growth%20Programme%20A4.pdf&quot; class=&quot;button&quot;&gt;Download Brochure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The benefits:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accelerated growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A robust and rigorous plan for growth&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More confidence and increased focus on priorities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The path to improved profitability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More effective leadership and management skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Drawing on the collective skills and knowledge of Grant Thornton’s extensive network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Retail Growth Programme is built around a series of growth workshops where you will develop and implement your growth strategy for your business. The programme is modular and allows you to continually apply your learning to how you run your business while you participate. The programme runs over 12 months. In between each workshop, you will continue working on developing and implementing your own growth strategy for your business, making immediate improvements every month.
Throughout the programme, you will be supported by an experienced account manager who works with you to ensure that you get the maximum value from your experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who is it for?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ambitious businesses in the retail sector&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it cost?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£5,000 + VAT (payable £1,250 + VAT per quarter)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does it take place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One monthly session in either London or Birmingham with support via phone and email across the duration of the programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-12-month-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YOUR 12 MONTH PROGRAMME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH SUPPORT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic conversation and growth reviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dedicated account manager providing coaching and support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly Peer Boards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quarterly insights on key sectors and trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GROWTH WORKSHOPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ten specially designed growth workshops for you to choose from a selection of sixteen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growth Planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Going International&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial Management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying and Merchandising&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Operations and Logistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;e-commerce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Customer and Sales Profiling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brand Identity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Engaging and Retaining Talent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reaching the Market&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing the Next Location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Retail Space Design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulations and Legislation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financing Growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme is designed for retailers or those looking to diversify into the retail sector. If you are already successfully trading and now want to take the next step towards future growth then please get in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;click-here-to-find-out-more-about-the-g-by-grant-thornton-retail-growth-programme&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the G by Grant Thornton Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>