<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.1.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://insideretail.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://insideretail.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-03-09T10:16:28+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/</id><title>Inside Retail</title><subtitle>The online destination for independent retailers. Whether you sell on the high street or online, are just getting started or tweaking the dream, you can find stories, tips, interviews and inspiration to help accelerate the growth of your business.</subtitle><entry><title>This is your growth year: How to take the next step</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/this-is-your-growth-year-how-to-take-the-next-step/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This is your growth year: How to take the next step" /><published>2017-02-15T12:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-15T12:28:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/this is your growth year - how to take the next step</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/this-is-your-growth-year-how-to-take-the-next-step/">&lt;p&gt;Back in November 2014, Alice Major started her company &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webuilt-thiscity.com/&quot;&gt;We Built this City &lt;/a&gt;as a ‘London souvenir revolution’. It began as an eight-week pop up shop in London’s Carnaby Street so that visitors and locals could ‘take home a unique and lasting piece of the city’. The pop-up went so well that they were invited back in Spring 2015 and are now a permanent fixture, being hailed by Time Out as the ‘Best Shop in Soho’.  They now have a collection of artwork and products from an impressive 250 creatives (plus some brilliant workshops and live events in store). We chat to Alice about her top tips for growth and how to drive your company forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;as-an-independent-retailer-what-have-you-found-to-be-your-biggest-obstacles-for-growth-and-how-have-you-overcome-them&quot;&gt;As an independent retailer what have you found to be your biggest obstacles for growth and how have you overcome them?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we first launched we had very limited start-up funding, so weren’t able to spend anything on traditional marketing. Instead we relied on PR contacts and the power of social media to build the brand and drive new customers into store. With such high footfall on Carnaby Street though, in the first eight weeks we decided to focus most of our energy on converting as many customers into store as possible - with live artists working in the window and giving away a free WBTC Gazette that mapped out our mission to revolutionise London souvenirs and introduced them to our creative community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a small team in the early days, we also knew we were going to struggle to launch our e-commerce store at the same time as the bricks and mortar store. We had to make a call to focus our limited resource on refining and growing sales in-store and delaying the online launch until we had our feet fully under the table on what is such a big retail opportunity on Carnaby. My biggest fear is taking too much on all at once and doing everything badly - better to take each step at a time, learn more about the customer and get it right. We’re just about to launch our online store after two years trading on Carnaby and we’re unbelievably excited to see the international growth that it will offer the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an independent retailer, you have to wear so many different hats until you can start expanding the team. That’s hard because you’re running in 100 different directions at once and can’t see how you’re going to grow anything without dedicated focus on each area. As soon as we had some money in the bank, I hired talented buyers across gifting and art - and a dedicated marketing manager. That’s given us an excellent start, but with over 600 SKUs and around 2000 people walking through our doors every day, the next critical hire is a merchandiser who can start digging into the sales data and helping us improve our product lifecycle. Retail is detail as they say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-you-are-time-pressed-what-are-your-pr-and-marketing-essentials&quot;&gt;When you are time pressed, what are your PR and marketing essentials?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We focus on the easy wins. We’ve worked hard over the last two years to develop some great relationships with journalists and influencers on London and travel titles which have had proven impact on footfall and sales. Targeted PR for us has always worked better than a scattergun approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also focus on keeping our Instagram community up to date with new products and artist collaborations - we focus particularly on Instagram because it has again proven to increase sales in-store. We’ve also been able to make a surprising number of online sales through the channel before launching our full e-commerce offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a creative retailer committed to supporting London artists, we also constantly seek to offer our customers ‘more than a transaction’ with a full programme of artist-led in-store events and workshops. This opens up a constant stream of additional PR and marketing opportunities for the brand and is a win-win for our artists and customers in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-considerations-would-you-make-when-hiring-your-first-member-of-staff&quot;&gt;What considerations would you make when hiring your first member of staff?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first store was a pop-up and we were given three weeks from the pitch to making it a reality, so hires had to be made incredibly quickly. I focused a lot on whether people could help me sell the brand and our artists in what was then going to be a very short two-month run. I now look for both that passion in the business, and our wider mission to help creatives, but also for people with nuts and bolts retail experience who have great attention to detail and can spot new opportunities for growth and improvement. Above all though, the most important attribute for me has to be that they 100% believe in your product and are excited to help you take it to the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="in-store" /><summary>Back in November 2014, Alice Major started her company We Built this City as a ‘London souvenir revolution’. It began as an eight-week pop up shop in London’s Carnaby Street so that visitors and locals could ‘take home a unique and lasting piece of the city’. The pop-up went so well that they were invited back in Spring 2015 and are now a permanent fixture, being hailed by Time Out as the ‘Best Shop in Soho’.  They now have a collection of artwork and products from an impressive 250 creatives (plus some brilliant workshops and live events in store). We chat to Alice about her top tips for growth and how to drive your company forward.</summary></entry><entry><title>Planning for investment in the year ahead: Big ticket spend for indie retailers - what’s worth it</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/big-ticket-spend-investment-for-the-year-ahead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning for investment in the year ahead: Big ticket spend for indie retailers - what&#39;s worth it" /><published>2017-02-15T11:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-15T11:25:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/big ticket spend investment for the year ahead</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/big-ticket-spend-investment-for-the-year-ahead/">&lt;p&gt;When running your own business there are so many added costs that come up that you sometimes just can’t quite account for. Particularly, when it comes to big ticket products. Big ticket products can be defined as ‘items that are of high value’ and, of course dependent on the size of your company and what you are selling, they vary greatly. For product designer Jinny Ngui, who runs her own ceramics business &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jinnyngui-design.com/home&quot;&gt;Jinny Ngui Design &lt;/a&gt;her big ticket spend came in the form of a kiln and for Highgate Flowers in came as a shop floor expansion. Here’s how they did it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-did-you-decide-to-invest-in-your-big-ticket-purchase&quot;&gt;When did you decide to invest in your big ticket purchase?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was freelancing I used to design and decorate tableware in my spare time. Back then I used to hire a kiln, when Pottery Crafts had a small warehouse in Battersea. I used to go to Pottery Crafts on a regular basis when I was studying. Sadly, when Pottery Crafts closed their London warehouse I occasionally asked friends if I could borrow their kilns, which I always felt guilty doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-did-you-prepare-to-make-your-big-ticket-purchase&quot;&gt;How did you prepare to make your big ticket purchase?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put my designs on hold for a while. One day I was talking with my mum about saving up for a kiln, but I had no idea where I could keep it or even if I could afford one. She kindly offered to lend me the money and let me keep the kiln at the bottom of the back garden. After lots of thinking about which kiln to get I got in touch with Pottery Crafts in Stoke-on-Trent. It look me a while to pay back my mum but it was such an achievement to pay it all off, plus I got to carry making while I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-did-it-change-your-business&quot;&gt;How did it change your business?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting my own kiln also made me re-evaluate how I bought my whiteware. Which up until then I bought in dribs and drabs from different places. I found a lovely company called Buttercup China. They offered small minimums and have also helped me decorate large orders, which I would have struggled to fulfil on my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if-big-ticket-spending-comes-in-the-form-of-shop-floor-expansion&quot;&gt;What if big ticket spending comes in the form of shop floor expansion?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the happy predicament that your business has grown so substantially you need bigger premises then it can be time to start looking for more ground space. For Highgate Flowers that was exactly the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Due to the success of the shop, we had too many customers and not enough space. The shop had evolved from just flowers to include selling plants as well to keep up with current trends. It then expanded to art installations in the windows and jewellery. Two years into the business, we decided it was time for growth. By focussing on expanding the shop, we’ve changed our working environment and are very happy to each have more space to work in. It’s also turned the shop into a much more family orientated area, so we can now accommodate prams. The new space has been really welcomed by our customers and is creating a lot of new business”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="in-store" /><summary>When running your own business there are so many added costs that come up that you sometimes just can’t quite account for. Particularly, when it comes to big ticket products. Big ticket products can be defined as ‘items that are of high value’ and, of course dependent on the size of your company and what you are selling, they vary greatly. For product designer Jinny Ngui, who runs her own ceramics business Jinny Ngui Design her big ticket spend came in the form of a kiln and for Highgate Flowers in came as a shop floor expansion. Here’s how they did it…</summary></entry><entry><title>How to find a work/life balance when you run your own retail business</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/life-balance-when-you-run-your-own-retail-business/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to find a work/life balance when you run your own retail business" /><published>2017-02-15T10:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-15T10:28:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/life balance when you run your own retail business</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/life-balance-when-you-run-your-own-retail-business/">&lt;p&gt;Opening your own shop is an absolute dream job for many. But just because you’re passionate about it doesn’t mean you’re suddenly immune to the demands of a seven-day daily grind and the sleepless nights that come with running a small business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With staffing costs likely to be the easiest thing to cut down on when you’re starting out, it can be tough finding a work/life balance that doesn’t leave you feeling like you exist only to open and close the shop doors, cramming ideas, exercise, your family, friends and (god forbid!) a social life into those short hours in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do people make it work? Alex Fitzpatrick opened a vintage shop called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/TheNewCuriosityShopHereford/&quot;&gt;The New Curiosity Shop&lt;/a&gt; in Hereford last July, swapping a high-pressure role as a commissioner for a local council for serving customers, antique hunting and a bit of consultancy on the side. The hours are long and the business is new, but Alex says she’s never felt better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘We decided to open the shop to reduce my stress levels and also to develop a career for my daughter. It has worked, because the stress of working all the hours God sends [in the shop] is nothing compared to working in an increasingly cash-strapped local authority trying to support vulnerable people,’ she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The best thing is being completely in control. We closed for a winter break [in January] and I went off to the Gower to clear out the cobwebs – a decision we were able to make at two days notice without asking anyone or worrying essential work was not happening because we weren’t there. And it was needed. We employ no other staff and worked 13 days straight up to Christmas, including a few late evening openings.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working day after day with weekends your busiest time can feel like you’re running on a treadmill of marathons with no means of jumping off. Alessandro Bonuzzi, with his business partner Tullio Nusca, opened &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/woofcoffee/&quot;&gt;Woof Coffee&lt;/a&gt; in Teddington, London last April. For the last nine months Alessandro has worked every single day, except Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I have been working every day. Every single day. It’s something I wouldn’t want for anyone else. It’s terrible. When you think about it it’s scary and terrible but the reality is worse. The good part is we only open 8am to 5pm. I used to work longer hours than this but at least I’m free in the evening,’ he says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does he do with those golden hours after 5pm? ‘I just go home and cook dinner. We started with a very small budget and until we reach a point where we can afford a payroll then we have to do the work ourselves,’ says Alessandro, a former sommelier and wine taster, who remains intensely passionate despite the slog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I don’t find it stressful. But I don’t want to say it’s relaxed because that would be untrue. Working everyday becomes part of your bodyclock. Every morning at 7am I open my eyes, because the business is open at 8am,’ he says. ‘I don’t walk down the street as I used to, because you look at competitors, you know. Looking at the signage, advertising, products. You always think “how can I do what I do better?”’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the thing about running a business like this: you have to be buyer, manager, marketing executive, brand developer and superhero - on top of ensuring the customer is always right, and that the machine delivers as it should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I’m always running ideas through my head,’ says &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.annawalkerlondon.com/&quot;&gt;Anna Walker&lt;/a&gt;, a handbag and accessories designer and maker who first launched an online store, but has since had a series of pop up shops in London. ‘I take work home with me, but it’s usually the creative things that I’ll work: design, problem solving and research rather than admin or order fulfilment. It’s what I love to do so it doesn’t really feel too much like work! I often post things on social media when I’m technically not “at work”. There is a part of my brain that’s never not working.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When not multitasking as ‘designer, production manager, sales person, PR, brand ambassador, etc’ Anna rebalances with the help of exercise and her support network. ‘I’ve recently taken up yoga which I am loving,’ she says. ‘I’ve never been very good at sticking to an exercise regime but I think that making sure that I dedicate time to my mind and my body every day is more rewarding than I ever thought it could be. Also my fiance and I are getting married later this year plus we are hopefully buying a flat so these are keeping [my priorities in line].’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaherazad Umbreen, the woman behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.18hourheels.com/&quot;&gt;18hourheels.com&lt;/a&gt;, an online store that raises money for charity, while also holding down a full-time job as head of marketing at The Co-Op, is so enthusiastic about her sideline business that it keeps her buoyed up despite her busy schedule. She also employs freelancers to help her out on the day-to-day tasks that she can’t do while working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I have to be super organised to achieve a happy balance in life - and so far I have,’ she says. ‘It’s stressful but it’s a really good kind of stress. When someone buys a pair of my shoes I dance with happiness. In a strange way, more stress equates to more happiness. Every pair of shoes sold supports the education of a woman or girl living in poverty.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘My business supported 500 women last year which makes me happy - but raises my stress levels somewhat as so many women are relying on me to sell shoes to help them. However, the benefit of running your own retail business is that you can fully control how much time you do spend. I commit to my time off with the same discipline that I commit to my work.  So, for example, when I go for a long weekend walk, I always leave my phone at home so that I am not distracted from my exercise.’&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inspiration" /><summary>Opening your own shop is an absolute dream job for many. But just because you’re passionate about it doesn’t mean you’re suddenly immune to the demands of a seven-day daily grind and the sleepless nights that come with running a small business.</summary></entry><entry><title>Ready For Growth?</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/Ready-For-Growth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ready For Growth?" /><published>2017-02-03T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-03T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/Ready For Growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/Ready-For-Growth/">&lt;p&gt;Independent retailers across the UK face a host of challenges and obstacles each and every day which can limit growth potential and often leave you feeling unsure of what the best steps towards growth are.
Inside Retail has conducted research into over 200 retailers like yourself from across the UK and we’ve found there are some recurring key challenges to achieving your business ambition. These challenges often include;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving traffic to your website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using social media to increase customer numbers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating work-life balance, and good business time management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Driving footfall to your shop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choosing products which sell fast at full price&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help address these issues and equip dynamic business leaders with the support they need to achieve their retail growth ambitions, we here at Inside Retail have teamed up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://g.grantthornton.co.uk/about-us/&quot;&gt;G by Grant Thornton&lt;/a&gt; to develop The Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme is designed with the leader of a retail businesses in mind; providing practical tools, plans and best practices that will help to facilitate rapid and sustainable business growth. 
It’s so important that time spent outside of your business brings with it tangible benefits both for you as an individual and for your business.  With this in mind, the 12 month programme you will allow you to develop your knowledge in key areas to deliver your business ambition, creating plans, networks and connections that will contribute to your business growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This programme provides a unique opportunity for retailers to step back from the day-to-day demands of running your business, giving you the clarity and the time to develop a detailed, actionable plan for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;click-here-to-find-out-more-about-the-g-by-grant-thornton-retail-growth-programmehttplpeventsascentialcomir-client-formsgrant-thornton-pagehtml&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/IR-Client-Forms_Grant-Thornton-Page.html&quot;&gt;Click here to find out more about the G by Grant Thornton Retail Growth Programme.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="marketing" /><summary>Independent retailers across the UK face a host of challenges and obstacles each and every day which can limit growth potential and often leave you feeling unsure of what the best steps towards growth are.
Inside Retail has conducted research into over 200 retailers like yourself from across the UK and we’ve found there are some recurring key challenges to achieving your business ambition. These challenges often include;</summary></entry><entry><title>Interview with Alexandra Shulman</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/interview-with-alexandra-shulman/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview with Alexandra Shulman" /><published>2017-02-01T12:08:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T12:08:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/interview-with-alexandra-shulman</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/interview-with-alexandra-shulman/">&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Shulman has edited British Vogue since 1992. During her time at Vogue, she has been awarded BSME Editor of the Year, PPA Editor of the Year award 2016, the WGSN Future 2016 Outstanding Achievement award and was granted an OBE in the 2005 New Year’s honours for her services to the magazine industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is a contributor to The Times, Daily Mail, Guardian and Daily Telegraph and has written two novels: Can We Still Be Friends? (2012) and The Parrots (2015). Inside Vogue: The Diary of my 100th Year was published by Fig Tree in October 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="inspiration" /><summary>Alexandra Shulman has edited British Vogue since 1992. During her time at Vogue, she has been awarded BSME Editor of the Year, PPA Editor of the Year award 2016, the WGSN Future 2016 Outstanding Achievement award and was granted an OBE in the 2005 New Year’s honours for her services to the magazine industry.</summary></entry><entry><title>Interview with Mary Portas</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/mary-portas-interview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview with Mary Portas" /><published>2017-02-01T11:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T11:32:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/mary portas interview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/mary-portas-interview/">&lt;p&gt;Retail expert Mary Portas, widely acknowledged as a leading authority on the sector, has advised government, transformed Harvey Nichols, and has produced a host of retail and business-themed TV programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A determined, passionate advocate of British retail, Mary is at the forefront of making the nation better consumers and the country’s shops better businesses. Her career started on the shop floor, rising through the ranks of John Lewis, Harrods and the Burton Group before being appointed Creative Director at Harvey Nichols. With the aid of cutting edge artists, designers, and a TV show called Absolutely Fabulous, Mary turned the store into a retail powerhouse and was on the board of the company by the age of 30. She has since worked with some of the world’s premier retail and product brands including Westfield, Clark’s, Dunhill, Louis Vuitton, Oasis Stores, Mercedes-Benz, and Boden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On television, Mary has presented on both BBC One, BBC2 and Channel 4. In Secret Shopper, she went undercover in some of the nation’s biggest retailers to expose the lack of customer service culture. In Mary, Queen of Shops she helped turn around struggling small retail businesses. She has also fronted series on charity shops, fashion, manufacturing, and her efforts to rejuvenate the high street. She’s also looked at retail and product trends in What Britain Buys and the lack of choice for older shoppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In speeches Mary discusses the changes in consumer behaviour as a result of the economy, the digital revolution and efforts to protect the environment. With critical insight, she examines how different retail sectors are responding and how brands of all shapes and sizes can best stand out. She also looks at the mistakes retailers make, and how to fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary is the author of How to Shop with Mary Queen of Shops, a book instructing readers on how to shop more efficiently, and also Windows: The Art of Retail Display. She has founded two retail consultancies working with both luxury and high street brands, and has launched her own fashion and footwear brands, and shop within House of Fraser. Mary also led an independent Government review into the regeneration of the high street.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="in-store" /><summary>Retail expert Mary Portas, widely acknowledged as a leading authority on the sector, has advised government, transformed Harvey Nichols, and has produced a host of retail and business-themed TV programmes.</summary></entry><entry><title>Preparing for Valentine’s and Mother’s Day</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/Preparing-for-Valentines-and-Mothers-Day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing for Valentine&#39;s and Mother’s Day" /><published>2017-02-01T09:16:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T09:16:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/Preparing for Valentines and Mothers Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/Preparing-for-Valentines-and-Mothers-Day/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-for-valentines-and-mothers-day&quot;&gt;Preparing for Valentine’s and Mother’s Day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carefully planned, Valentine’s Day and Mother’s Day can herald a welcome end to the post-Christmas quiet period for independents. So how should you prepare for two of the most important events in the retail calendar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan-early-but-not-too-early&quot;&gt;Plan early… but not too early&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Timely reminders of upcoming events are an important aspect of preparing for Valentine’s Day and Mother’s Day, because emotionally-engaging reminders can consistently trigger impulse purchases, according to retail psychologist Phillip Adcock, founder of the shopper research agency &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sbxl.com&quot;&gt;Shopping Behaviour Xplained Ltd&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet Adcock cautions that many retailers start advertising too early: “Give customers time to remember and make plans for event days, but avoid mixing Valentine’s Day products with Easter products (or Christmas with Halloween), as this dilutes their appeal, making the event seem a long way off, rather than just around the corner.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-overstock&quot;&gt;Don’t overstock&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under-stock and you risk missing the sales opportunities posed by the seasons of lovers and mothers, but overstock and you might regret it for some time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Over-committing to stock is probably the most risky part of planning for special occasions,” says &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poppytreffry.co.uk&quot;&gt;Poppy Treffry&lt;/a&gt;, textile designer and founder of the eponymous gift and homeware stores and online shop. She believes it’s critical to know what customers are likely to spend on Mother’s Day and Valentine’s Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Our shops are very coastal – they are busiest during summer – whereas Valentine’s Day is a fairly quiet time of year, so we have to be careful,” she says. Treffry recommends using market research to better understand your customers. “We used Survey Monkey for this and then planned stock levels accordingly, and the information we gathered about our customers was extremely useful.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin Cook, SME consultant for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessdoctors.co.uk&quot;&gt;Business Doctors&lt;/a&gt; says the best way for established businesses to avoid overstocking is to base purchasing decisions on past sales figures, mindful that the rate of sale tends to “plummet back to normal” after such events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you’re facing your first Valentine’s Day or Mother’s Day as an independent retailer? Cook still advises erring on the side of caution when it comes to stock: “Unless you’re a florist, it’s unlikely that your turnover will double in the weeks leading up to Valentine’s or Mother’s Day. Better to buy a little and sell out, than have a shop full of love-themed products filling your shelves until next Christmas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-underestimate-visual-merchandising&quot;&gt;Don’t underestimate visual merchandising&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few retailers forget the importance of an appealing shop window, yet many overlook more subtle visual merchandising techniques. Adcock advises putting front-of-store displays at the forefront of your VM strategy, because they put shoppers “in a positive frame of mind by triggering emotional recognition”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Themed displays throughout the store can also interrupt the ‘shopping coma’ that many shoppers fall into,” he says. “Using these displays to make choosing gifts easy — categorising them as ‘funny’ or ‘romantic’, for example — reduces any difficulty shoppers have in choosing the perfect present.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reminding customers of Valentine’s Day when they arrive is tactical, since the typical shopper impulse-buys for others at the start of the shop and for themselves towards the end, according to Adcock. “Even if they are part of the 38% who aren’t planning to celebrate it, they may be reminded to pick up a bottle of wine or treat for their significant other.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;go-the-extra-mile&quot;&gt;Go the extra mile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating time for your customers can be difficult at peak busy times but Elaine Burns, creative director at &lt;a href=&quot;www.weareponymous.com&quot;&gt;Wear Eponymous&lt;/a&gt; – an independent fashion and lifestyle retailer focused on both e-commerce and pop-up shops – recommends planning for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Be prepared to chat with customers one-on-one if they require assurance on a significant purchase for someone special,” she says. “They deserve your genuine, undivided attention to ensure that they have faith in their purchase and their questions are properly answered. It’s the least you can do, and makes all the difference between you and a mass-market retailer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valentine’s Day is one of the biggest dates in the calendar for Sarah Connelly, owner of Edinburgh-based award-winning lingerie boutique &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.odysseyboutique.co.uk&quot;&gt;Odyssey&lt;/a&gt;, but she gives a nod to the season, rather than re-stocking for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Odyssey is built on representing the most luxurious and exciting lingerie year-round, so I don’t worry about alienating my non-Valentine’s clients at this time of year. Instead, I create window displays and in-store merchandising that acknowledge the occasion, whilst inspiring everyone to experiment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dont-neglect-social-media&quot;&gt;Don’t neglect social media&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From PR and social media to local events and advertising, no stone should be left unturned in telling the world about upcoming seasonal promotions. But don’t focus so heavily on planning for sales that you overlook the value of building a buzz around your brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Special events can make a major impact on sales throughout the year, providing reasons for shoppers to buy extra products,” says Adcock. “Even if they aren’t buying from the special displays, there may well be an uplift in sales — especially if you are giving away themed samples in-store, which can increase sales by around 10%.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Significant occasions in the retail calendar give you the opportunity to ramp up your activity around a theme,” agrees Cook. “Think about prize giveaways, good news stories, blogs commenting on fashion or gift trends – all of which tell your customers you are ready and waiting to help them with their buying dilemmas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cater-for-everyone--within-reason&quot;&gt;Cater for everyone – within reason&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have been eating, breathing and sleeping all things hearts-and-flowers for months, but that doesn’t mean your customers are enamoured with the season. Cater, too, for those who aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Many inexperienced retailers misjudge the size and scope of their Valentine’s Day displays, hiding them away without advertising or allowing them to overrun the store, excluding shoppers who may not be interested in those items,” says Adcock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, though, it’s important to remember that you can’t please everyone all of the time. “In retail it’s very easy to lose focus, which can weaken the overall impact of your efforts, but instead of trying to cater for fathers on Mother’s Day, keep the focus unashamedly on customers looking to buy something tied to the seasonal event,” says Ali Ridha Jaffar, sales director of online photo gift retailer &lt;a href=&quot;printerpix.co.uk&quot;&gt;Printerpix&lt;/a&gt;. “There are at least 360 other days in the year to focus on everyone else, so be bold; experiment with the opportunity and see what it yields.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="in-store" /><summary>Preparing for Valentine’s and Mother’s Day
Carefully planned, Valentine’s Day and Mother’s Day can herald a welcome end to the post-Christmas quiet period for independents. So how should you prepare for two of the most important events in the retail calendar?</summary></entry><entry><title>How to make the most of February</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/How-to-make-the-most-of-February/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to make the most of February" /><published>2017-02-01T08:58:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-01T08:58:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/How to make the most of February</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/How-to-make-the-most-of-February/">&lt;p&gt;By Jackie Mitchell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, February is a quiet month (apart from Valentine’s Day) following a hectic Christmas, so how do you make the most of this fallow period to make 2017 a profitable year? We asked several retailers, both online and offline, how they spend February:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Woolley from Paper High uses the month to wind down, tie up loose ends, place orders and plan the buying cycle. “We welcome the month to be quiet. We check our stock, tidy up and get everything sorted out. We’re not actively trying to drum up trade as we need this month to plan. We have a new brochure and price list coming out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February is an ideal month to go on any buying trips. Woolley is travelling to India and Nepal to buy new products. Since the company moved to a larger warehouse, they can consider bigger products. “So we’ll be looking at mirrors, big wire ducks, outdoor ornaments. When we had a smaller warehouse, we were limited, but now our eyes will be open to anything when we visit India and Nepal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Product development is high on the agenda for Ned Trier at The Gluttonous Gardener. “We create our own products from scratch. February is a busy preparation month when we can sit back after the chaos of Christmas and get a bit more organised. We work with various nurseries in Europe who grow plants for us. We speak to them to ascertain the sizes and quantities we’d like to use. We buy most of our nursery stock when the plants are still dormant – we’ve already done most of that, although we buy a last batch in February.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The month presents an opportunity to get practical jobs done such as the painting of the warehouse floor and laying a new stair carpet in the office. “We’re in the nursery sorting out the flooded areas and putting in new gravel,” he adds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February is a great month for planning marketing activities. Trier says they are planning their marketing for Mother’s Day and Father’s Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all retailers will be quiet in February. Marie Truelove, owner of Truelove, a lingerie shop in Barnes, will be capitalising on all the publicity surrounding Valentine’s Day to boost business. “In the run up there will be press articles about finding your perfect bra size and so on, so you need to take advantage of that and ride that wave. We’re making a “Window of Love” display with a giant heart motif and asking our customers to write a message to their loved one on a post it note which will be stuck on. We’ll be holding a special event on the day offering customers a glass of champagne and introducing our spring and summer lingerie collections.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truelove uses Valentine’s Day as a reminder to her customers it’s time for them to review their lingerie drawer. “We also sell swimwear in February as we find many people are going on holiday – many more than last year. February can be a bad month if you don’t do something about it. You need to give customers a nice surprise.”&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Inspiration" /><summary>By Jackie Mitchell</summary></entry><entry><title>How to get Close to your Customer</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/how-to-get-close-to-your-customer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to get Close to your Customer" /><published>2017-01-09T13:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-09T13:10:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/how to get close to your customer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/how-to-get-close-to-your-customer/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;knowing-your-customer&quot;&gt;Knowing Your Customer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Independent retailers have always prided themselves on being close to their customers. But in today’s increasingly complex world, this has become much harder to achieve. Technology can now play a powerful role in restoring that close relationship with customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retailers place great importance on their ability to know their customers. This is based on their ability to collate data and use it to gain insights on their customer base which can then be used to deliver a better experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting this data and being able to crunch the numbers through data analytics has very much been the domain of larger organisations but with the advent of cloud-based solutions such as Vend it is now possible for smaller retailers to cost effectively
enjoy the same benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-analytics-powers-loyalty&quot;&gt;Data analytics powers loyalty&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlie Yates, owner of Candle Scentral in Worthing explains how his belief in the power of loyalty has brought powerful results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaining insight into its customers through a loyalty programme has massively benefited candle specialist Candle Scentral, that is now able to target these individuals through tailored emails and in-store ‘clientelling’ using tablets.
The multi-channel retailer uses the loyalty tool within the Vend solution to collect customers’ details and subsequently mine their shopping history data to determine how best to market to them – both online and in-store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;better-planning-for-seasonal-joy&quot;&gt;Better Planning for Seasonal Joy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge is definitely power when it comes to using data to take away the risk and unpredictability of the key retail seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christmas remains a very predictable event in the annual calendar but such is the changing nature of the festive period, with pre-season sales and new events emerging like Black Friday, it has become very difficult for retailers to accurately forecast
demand and to optimise their buying. Research from Inside Retail has found that 49% of retailers find…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-learn-more-about-the-power-of-data-sign-up-here-for-the-full-reporthttplpeventsascentialcominside-retail-power-of-datahtml&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lp.events.ascential.com/Inside-Retail-Power-of-Data.html&quot;&gt;To learn more about the power of data sign up here for the full report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="in-store" /><summary>Knowing Your Customer</summary></entry><entry><title>Planning For January</title><link href="http://insideretail.com/articles/planning-for-january/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning For January" /><published>2016-12-08T11:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-08T11:47:00+00:00</updated><id>http://insideretail.com/articles/planning-for-january</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://insideretail.com/articles/planning-for-january/">&lt;p&gt;Retail is a dynamic sector where change is a constant. One thing is certain though, Christmas 2017 starts on January 1st in what is a crucial month for independent retailers. Armed with the facts and figures from the Christmas season just past and a fresh perspective on what makes customers and your business tick, it’s time to take a deep breath and prep for the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;be-forensic&quot;&gt;Be Forensic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensuring a good 2017 comes down to planning. Poor planning often results in poor performance but January is the time for independent retailers to take a forensic look at all the aspects of Christmas 2016, evaluate what happened and why, and then plan ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review&quot;&gt;Review&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with what sold. What were the bestsellers? Did you run out too soon? And look at what’s still in the store or in the warehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond product, there are many aspects of a retail business that can make or break the year. Zoom in on elements such as staffing and pick-and-pack productivity. Did you have the right staff, in the right numbers, at the right time? What working hours need to be extended or reduced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Review promotional activity, customer communications and marketing. Which social media platforms worked? What could you amplify next year? How can you build up relationships with newly engaged customers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measure&quot;&gt;Measure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measure and understand how discounts and seasonal sales events impacted sales and margins. Black Friday is a relative newcomer to the British retail landscape and as such is still evolving. What that means long-term is unclear but for many customers it’s become a weekend event that kickstarts their Christmas shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan&quot;&gt;Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve thoroughly reviewed what happened, indies need to plan just as thoroughly ahead. Where things went wrong, how can you ensure that doesn’t happen again? When it comes to successes, are there learnings from one part of the retail business that could be applied to another?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prioritise&quot;&gt;Prioritise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it pays to be realistic. For indies it’s impossible to do everything, so the review and planning process inevitably means prioritising. Look at what can be achieved with the resources at hand, what are the improvements you can make that will really move the dial for you next time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;go-buying&quot;&gt;Go Buying&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January is also the time to start buying for Christmas 2017. Consider not only which product sold well but also what shoppers requested or searched for online that you didn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For first-time retailers in particular it’s hard to judge what will be a bestseller but a proper and honest performance review will help build up confidence and encourage boldness when buying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;january-counts-too&quot;&gt;January Counts Too&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For store-based retailers, don’t forget the significance of January too. In some locations the January sale can have a big impact on clearing stock and is a chance to attract customers who’ve been away over the Christmas period itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure shelves are not empty and windows are fresh. Plan some events for January and update with new stock. It’s a month for introducing new ideas and sowing the seed for the months and year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="ecommerce" /><summary>Retail is a dynamic sector where change is a constant. One thing is certain though, Christmas 2017 starts on January 1st in what is a crucial month for independent retailers. Armed with the facts and figures from the Christmas season just past and a fresh perspective on what makes customers and your business tick, it’s time to take a deep breath and prep for the year ahead.</summary></entry></feed>
